<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Portfolio on Portfolio</title>
    <link>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Portfolio on Portfolio</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tenure_promotion/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Statements of support</title>
      <link>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/testimonials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/testimonials/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;colleagues&#34;&gt;Colleagues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following are letters of support from colleagues with whom I have collaborated during my probationary period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../files/Bergen support forsyth.pdf&#34;&gt;Diane Forsyth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../files/Hines_letter.pdf&#34;&gt;Jake Hines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../files/Bergen_2018_Letter.pdf&#34;&gt;Allison Quam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;students&#34;&gt;Students&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;../../img/letter1.PNG&#39;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/letter1.PNG&#34; width=&#34;200&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;../../img/letter2.PNG&#39;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/letter2.PNG&#34; width=&#34;200&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Jimmy Hickey went above and beyond in his &lt;a href=&#34;https://jimmyjhickey.github.io/silas&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;gracious support of my application&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criterion 1: Teaching Effectiveness</title>
      <link>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit1/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;outline&#34;&gt;Outline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#sec1&#34;&gt;What is effective teaching?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#sec2&#34;&gt;I taught statistical thinking, integrating real data with a context and purpose&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#sec3&#34;&gt;I fostered active learning in all my statistics classes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#sec4&#34;&gt;I mapped student learning outcomes to GEP Goal 4 criteria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#sec7&#34;&gt;I implemented computational problem-solving in upper-level statistics courses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#sec5&#34;&gt;I developed curricula for DSCI 310 and taught its first three offerings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#sec6&#34;&gt;I was a motivating, passionate, and helpful instructor in all my courses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005 I embarked on a double-major in statistics and piano
performance at Winona State. The former was obviously necessary to facilitate my current career, but so much of my professional activity during my
probationary period reminds me of the latter. During my time as a piano
performance major, I would spend hours each day in the
practice room perfecting Chopin ballades, Bach suites, or Beethoven
sonatas. I&amp;rsquo;ll never forget the memory of playing through a piece for the
first time: an experience simultaneously disheartening and invigorating.
My fingers were wooden twigs, I played more wrong notes than right,
the tempo mangled in starts and fits. Even still, deeply frustrated by the first sight-read, I could catch
glimpses of the potential for profound beauty if I just kept practicing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, I would. Over weeks, the easier passages became fluid as my fingers memorized their roles. Eventually I could
play most of the piece smoothly and keep tempo comfortably for
most of the piece. But the devilish passages persisted
in causing trouble. So I zoomed in on these, spending hours on only a few measures, repeating and repeating the
troublesome passages until even the most
creased wrinkles were smoothed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this sound like teaching? It does to me! It&amp;rsquo;s part of the
infinitely baffling and rewarding dance that is life as an educator.
After 4+ years teaching statistics and data science courses at Winona
State, I have smoothed out many of the wrinkles. And yet I have the
distinct feeling that no matter how long I work at it, there will always
be more wrinkles to smooth. Or more likely, a wrinkle that I thought was
smooth that when viewed from a new perspective I see is smooth no
longer. And this is part of the joy of it all: there will never cease to
be opportunities for creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I firmly believe that a quality teacher cannot be static. I
am most effective the quicker and the more thoroughly I reflect upon my
teaching and act upon my reflections. The day I claim to &amp;ldquo;have arrived&amp;rdquo;
on the peak of perfection is the day I cease to be an effective teacher.
Over the years, this growth mindset has been both painful and
indispensable. I am thankful for where it has taken me over the past
four years, and excited to see where it will take me in the years to
come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have high standards. Of my students, I expect thorough, careful work
and thought. I have very low tolerance for sloppy or half-hearted
efforts. But as high as my expectations are for my students, they are
much higher for myself. Never does a day pass but I am reflecting on
ways I can improve as a teacher. The following narrative of my teaching
effectiveness summarizes the layers upon layers of modifications and
improvements accumulated in my teaching approaches over the years. These
source from places as various as a conversation with a colleague,
intuition rising on a walk home from work, or a question posed by a
student that framed something in a way I had never thought to look. For
all the people, places, and conversations that have shaped me and
contributed to my professional and personal growth over the recent
years: I am thankful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;sec1&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-effective-teaching&#34;&gt;What is effective teaching?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following narrative is supposed to provide evidence of my ability to
teach effectively. As I reflected on this it became evident that
I needed a rubric against which to define effective teaching. To
this end I turned to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amstat.org/asa/files/pdfs/GAISE/GaiseCollege_Full.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2016 Guidelines for Assessment and Instruction
in Statistics Education (GAISE) college
report&lt;/a&gt;.
This report was published by our professional organization, the American
Statistical Association (ASA) and vetted by many national leaders in
college-level statistics education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GAISE college report contains six recommendations for effective
statistics education at the college level:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teach statistical thinking.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teach statistics as an investigative process of problem-solving and
  decision-making.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give students experience with multivariable thinking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on conceptual understanding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrate real data with a context and a purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foster active learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use technology to explore concepts and analyze data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use assessments to improve and evaluate student learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It follows that an effective statistics educator should incorporate
these recommendations in their teaching. In the following narrative I
provide specific evidence of ways I have done exactly that during my
time as a probationary faculty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;sec2&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-1&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-taught-statistical-thinking-integrating-real-data-with-a-context-and-purpose&#34;&gt;I taught statistical thinking, integrating real data with a context and purpose&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember my first-ever statistics class which I took at a community
college. We calculated means and standard deviations &amp;ldquo;by hand.&amp;rdquo; Homework
questions gave us summary information like mean, sample size, and
standard error and had us calculate test statistics and p-values from
scratch. We wrote statistical conclusions like &amp;ldquo;we reject the null
hypothesis&amp;rdquo; with no further context. This approach to statistics
education did very little to stimulate statistical thinking or to frame
statistics as an investigative process of problem-solving and
decision-making. I am fortunate to be surrounded by colleagues at Winona
State who robustly implement the first GAISE recommendation to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;teach
statistical thinking&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Thanks to their influence and mentorship I have
found it very natural to follow this recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it impossible to extricate the first and third GAISE
recommendations. To me, exposing students to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;statistical thinking&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
(R1) is nearly always facilitated by &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;integrating real data with a
context and a purpose&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (R3). Accordingly, the following sections serve
to provide evidence of how I have followed both the first and the third
GAISE report recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-taught-statistics-as-an-investigative-process-of-problem-solving-and-decision-making&#34;&gt;I taught statistics as an investigative process of problem-solving and decision making&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will find no examples in my assignments of asking students to
hand-calculate standard deviations or provide context-barren
conclusions. Regardless of the level of the class, my homework
assignments and assessments are centered around a research question that
has context and is to be investigated with real data. This helps
students see statistics as a powerful way to answer important questions,
rather than a disconnected collection of methods and tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are examples of homework assignments across a spectrum of classes.
Even though the &lt;em&gt;tools&lt;/em&gt; (the statistical tests or analyses) used in the
assignments are different, and range from introductory to advanced, each
assignment contains a research question about real data with a context
and requires the student to make a conclusion about the research
question in the context of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;STAT 110

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/0apb8ac59jx7cxb/Stat110-chisquare.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;chi-square
test&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/ypf5q0sjxgka79g/Stat110-ttest.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;t-test&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/0kh137oc7wvo1ta/Stat110-regression.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;simple linear
regression&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;STAT 310&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/k64yb0yc17ms2ui/Stat310-MLR.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;multiple linear
regression&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/h6wwlasgy1gnopu/Stat310-MLR-interaction.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Regression with an
interaction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/e7htuni2a0aam8c/Stat310-logistic.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Logistic
regression&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;STAT 365&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/31vermqlwus4n0o/Stat365-anova.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Analysis of
variance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/6k9u2l5er8yv8bw/Stat365-ancova.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Analysis of
covariance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/2cl0v0p9i3181nb/Stat365-mixed_model_w_interaction.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mixed model with
interaction&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-gave-students-experience-with-multivariable-thinking&#34;&gt;I gave students experience with multivariable thinking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This recommendation is more relevant to introductory statistics courses
(STAT 110 and 210) than for upper-level courses, as multivariable thinking is a given in upper-level courses whereas the STAT 110/210 level historically includes only bivariate thinking. During my probationary period I have sought to
incorporate much more multivariable thinking in my introductory
statistics courses including ideas of &amp;ldquo;adjusting for&amp;rdquo; a third variable
and thinking about confounders (a third variable that influences the
relationship between two primary variables of interest). I provide some
examples of this below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;STAT 110&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/xrkraz9byqd5gpe/4%20-Confounding%20and%20study%20types.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Notes on confounding&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;https://mediaspace.minnstate.edu/media/0_bq3gwgld&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Accompanying video quiz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/sywz338i1gdhoku/12%20-%20Adjusted%20measures%20of%20association.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Notes on adjusting for confounder&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;https://mediaspace.minnstate.edu/media/0_m1262svg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Video quiz 1&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;https://mediaspace.minnstate.edu/media/0_q0hrkg1a&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Video Quiz 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/amezndw8gzxvppo/Stat110-adjusting.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Multivariable assignment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;STAT 210

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/413uzjwh9x9xk10/Stat210-confounding.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Confounding problem&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;sec3&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-2&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-fostered-active-learning-in-all-my-statistics-classes&#34;&gt;I fostered active learning in all my statistics classes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth recommendation from the GAISE report is to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;foster active
learning.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; In this section I provide evidence of the many ways in
which I have implemented this recommendation in my teaching, using many
different cutting-edge teaching technology tools to assist me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-used-top-hat-to-improve-in-class-student-engagement-in-stat-110-and-210&#34;&gt;I used Top Hat to improve in-class student engagement in STAT 110 and 210&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon arriving at Winona State in 2014, I was met with an extremely
innovative, simulation-based approach to teaching the introductory
statistics content of our STAT 110 and STAT 210 that was developed and
spearheaded by my colleagues. This approach has been recognized as
effective at national conferences and in publications for several years.
I was the beneficiary of this well-developed and effective curricula and
endeavored to develop a method of presentation that built upon these
conceptual frameworks while fostering student engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of Spring 2018, Winona State offered a free license to Top Hat, an
instant response system wherein students are posed a question with
multiple choices. They respond, and the responses are summarized
instantaneously. This facilitates greater student engagement during
lecture while also allowing me to quickly address misconceptions when
many students answer a question incorrectly. I have spent a significant
amount of time over the years developing and refining gap-style
PowerPoint notes with multiple choice questions that I would pose in
class for student engagement and discussion. Two examples are available
below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/nt7jh4t75cwyzb0/5%20-%20Populations%20and%20samples.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example PowerPoint 1
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/qz9uu1queflpiyh/7%20-%20Hypothesis%20testing.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example PowerPoint
2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure below summarizes student responses to the statement &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Top Hat
was helpful in my understanding of the course material&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; posed on
end-of-semester course evaluations. The responses are percent who
strongly agreed, agreed, disagreed, or strongly disagreed with the
statement. The percentages shown are out of 427 student responses. Over
85% of students either strongly agreed or agreed that Top Hat helped
them understand the course material:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../../../img/tophat.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, several students mentioned Top Hat as one of the things
they liked most about the course. Below are some selected responses to
the statement &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The thing I liked MOST about the course was&amp;hellip;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;that we did top hat questions during class. it gave me a reason to actually go back in the notes and try to answer the question to try to understand the material.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;top hat, it allowed me to think through the material before actually learning it through the homework.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;top hat, practice problems, the clarity of the material and the professor.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tophat and powerpoints to follow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Top hat questions!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;using top hat in class to better understand examples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;top hat, interesting lectures&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I am horrible at anything math related, I have always done horribly in math classes. but, because you were so good at explaining things, and kept us engaged by implementing tophat, I was able to stay focused during the entire lecture and my mind wouldn&amp;rsquo;t wander off like it usually would in other math classes i&amp;rsquo;ve taken.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final response above speaks to an increased level of engagement.
I am pleased that some students recognized that
the use of Top Hat kept them better engaged during class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#39;crowdgrader&#39;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-implemented-crowdgrader-to-facilitate-peer-evaluation&#34;&gt;I implemented CrowdGrader to facilitate peer evaluation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first began to think about the benefits of peer evaluation after
hearing a &lt;a href=&#34;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/JSM/2015/onlineprogram/AbstractDetails.cfm?abstractid=317412&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;talk by Dennis
Sun&lt;/a&gt;
at the 2015 Joint Statistical Meetings in Seattle, WA. I have since
incorporated peer evaluation in several of my courses, most
significantly in STAT 210 and DSCI 310. I will describe its usage in
DSCI 310 in a subsequent section. Here, I focus on its use in STAT 210,
as this represents my most significant implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By August 2015 I had taught three sections of STAT 210, and I was at a
point with this course where I was putting immense amounts of work into
providing student feedback but not seeing the students engage with the
feedback and improve from it. After hearing &lt;a href=&#34;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/JSM/2015/onlineprogram/AbstractDetails.cfm?abstractid=317412&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dennis
Sun&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s
JSM talk, I decided to implement peer review in my STAT 210 sections by
way of the free (at the time) web site
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crowdgrader.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CrowdGrader.org&lt;/a&gt;. Thus beginning in Fall
2015, each homework assignment consisted of a submission phase, a review
phase, and a feedback phase. During the submission phase, students
completed their homework assignment and uploaded their submission in a
Word document to CrowdGrader. The review phase then commenced, during
which students reviewed and graded 4-5 randomly assigned blinded
submissions using a rubric-key that I provided. During the feedback
phase, students could then see and evaluate the grades and reviews they
received on their own submission. Their final grade on the submission
was a weighted average of: A) the crowd-graded scores on their own
submission; B) completing peer reviews of their assigned submissions; C)
the reliability of the peer review. As the instructor, I was able to see
the entire process and weigh in on highly variable grades or assignments
with a low number of peer grades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The peer review process seemed to offer several advantages to address
the lack of student engagement with the feedback I was giving;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students are required to engage with the assignment key (which
doubles as a grading rubric).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students are exposed to a variety of problem-solving approaches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students receive more feedback on assignments than from just the
professor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students see work of varying levels of quality. Seeing
higher-quality work can improve motivation, while seeing
lower-quality work can increase a sense of solidarity when students
see that they are not the &amp;ldquo;only ones&amp;rdquo; who struggle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The peer review process nontrivially increased the amount of work
required of students on each homework assignment, which was a common
complaint on course evaluations. Nevertheless, my intuition about the
benefits of the process was borne out in some student responses to the
prompt &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;State one aspect about evaluating your peers&amp;rsquo; homework
assignments that you found beneficial.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Selected responses are shown
below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Repeatedly having to go over the CORRECT answers for questions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Looking over other people&amp;rsquo;s work and seeing where they made mistakes helped make sure that I didn&amp;rsquo;t make the same mistake&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I got to see how other people figured out the problems. Everyone has a different thinking process, so I found that beneficial to help me solve the problems differently.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If majority of students didn&amp;rsquo;t answer the same question it felt better that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t the only one who didn&amp;rsquo;t understand the question.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Got to see many different ways of doing it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;if you didn&amp;rsquo;t get it, others could have showed you how it was done&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I was able to see other peoples thought process and how they either got the question right or wrong&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;getting to see what the prof was looking for in the answers, which helped on the test&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Being forced to see the problems an extra five times made them really stick in my head.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It helped me to critically think about what was really correct.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It helped me know where I went wrong in my own homework and helped me know what kind of responses the professor was looking for.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, many of these responses came from students who complained
about the amount of time and work involved in the peer-review process.
These students nevertheless were able to identify several of its key
learning advantages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;flipit&#34;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-entirely-flipped-the-stat-110-classroom&#34;&gt;I entirely flipped the STAT 110 classroom.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beginning in Spring Semester 2017 and continuing through Fall 2017, I
taught STAT 110, our primary service course on introductory statistics,
in a &amp;ldquo;partially flipped&amp;rdquo; fashion. In a typical week of a
Tuesday/Thursday course, one class period was devoted to lecturing with
instant student quizzing using the aforementioned Top Hat. The other
class period was dedicated to group homework. I liked the idea of
devoting class time to group homework for a number of reasons. As an
instructor, I can hear students discussing and arguing about concepts
with each other. I am also able to provide on-the-spot assistance much
more efficiently. Implementing group homework seemed to work well, and
in course evaluations students tended to Strongly agree or Agree with
the statement &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I like that homework was done in groups in class&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Responses from Spring-Fall 2017 course evaluations &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/grouphw-bar.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word cloud below summarizes student responses to the question &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What
did you like BEST about in-class group homework?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/grouphw-wordcloud.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words that stand out include &amp;ldquo;ask&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;questions,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;help,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;bounce ideas,&amp;rdquo; all aspects that I intuited as advantages of in-class group
homework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even though I had cut back to lecturing only half of the
designated class period, I was still dissatisfied by the inefficiencies
I identified in my lecture delivery method. Drawbacks of in-class
lecture delivery included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rushed/prolonged note-taking pauses. My lecture notes are &amp;ldquo;gap
style,&amp;rdquo; implying students must be in class to complete conceptual
gaps that I provide in class. A typical scenario included me filling
in the gap notes, proceeded by students frantically copying my words
into their notes. Some students finished faster than others and had
to wait around for the slower students to finish. I never knew how
well or accurately students transcribed my ideas into their notes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inefficiency when giving instructions on how to use computer
software. STAT 110 includes heavy use of software including JMP for
data analyses and Tinkerplots or StatKey for carrying out simulation
studies. Students need thorough step-by-step instructions as they
encounter these programs for the first time. Inevitably upon
presenting these steps, even though I provided detailed screenshots
in the notes, students would ask to &amp;ldquo;see the steps again.&amp;rdquo; This
resulted in a class slow-down as I would repeat the instructions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Content gaps when students miss class. Even the most industrious
students sometimes miss class due to unforeseen circumstances. If
the only medium of content delivery is in class, these students are
robbed of valuable learning if life circumstances necessitate
missing a class or two. Getting notes from their peers is not the
same as receiving the content from their instructor. These content
gaps are particularly detrimental in a course like Stat 110 where
concepts continue to build throughout the semester.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inconsistent lecture delivery. I am not equally sharp at all points
in the day! If I had an 8am section of Stat 110, often I would feel
dull during lecture delivery. Late-morning or early afternoon
lectures were much sharper. Ideally, students should experience an
equally high-quality content delivery regardless of what time of day
they are taking the course.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, during Spring Semester 2018, I spent an enormous amount of
time fully flipping Stat 110. The final product resulted in 100% of
content delivered exclusively through online lecture video quizzes that
students watched outside class, with the newly-freed class time devoted
to working on and solving problems. My work around flipping centered on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creating high-quality video quizzes to deliver course content. Using
Camtasia Studio, I could record, edit, and produce high-quality
video lectures. The PowerPoint slides I developed over the years
included many multiple-choice questions that I previously asked in
class using Top Hat. These questions very naturally transitioned to
video quiz questions, where the video periodically pauses for the
students to answer a multiple choice question. The result is a suite
of videos that I believe are succinct, engaging, and thorough. The
two examples below illustrate how portions of the lecture previously
delivered in-class using Top Hat have now transitioned to video quiz
questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mediaspace.minnstate.edu/media/Stat+110-+Lecture+5A+populations+and+samples/0_xglk64n0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example Video 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example Video 2

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mediaspace.minnstate.edu/media/Stat+110-+Lecture+7A+hypothesis+testing%2C+part+1+-+Quiz/0_e4iyo8pf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mediaspace.minnstate.edu/media/Stat+110-+Lecture+7A+hypothesis+testing%2C+part+2+-+Quiz/0_vpnyrwkx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mediaspace.minnstate.edu/media/Stat+110-+Lecture+7A+hypothesis+testing+examples+-+Quiz/0_i6q35d42&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creating D2L practice quizzes to reinforce the concepts delivered in
videos. Students could take these quizzes as many times as they
liked after watching the videos.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creating D2L quizzes that students took in class weekly. These
quizzes often included at least some of the questions on the
practice quizzes. These in-class quizzes incentivized students to
watch the videos and take the practice quiz, and gave me regular
individualized assessments that did not impose too great a grading
burden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creating additional practice problems that gave practice with
higher-level problem solving including obtaining and interpreting
computer output and writing conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the new fully-flipped class, the in-class time I previously spent
lecturing is now fully dedicated to completion of the higher-level
practice problems and a weekly D2L quiz. Not only has this approach
addressed the drawbacks of in-class delivery outlined above, it has also
provided many more opportunities for students to practice problem
solving than my previous versions of Stat 110. The practice D2L quizzes,
in-class quizzes, and practice problems are all new introductions into
Stat 110, in addition to the group homework I was already using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preliminary responses on student evaluations seem very positive about
the flipped model. Below are some student responses to the prompt
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The thing I liked MOST about the course was&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, taken from Spring 2018 course evaluations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That we got to watch the lectures at home, where we could play them back and take as long as we wanted taking notes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The professor and his dedication. I loved the flipped course as well (problems in class, lectures outside).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;the flipped design of the course&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;doing the lectures outside of class&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I thoroughly enjoyed the lecture videos. Very clear and concise.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Flip classroom. Very convenient for a math course.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Homework in class and lectures on our own&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;the hybrid aspect&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How it was reversed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of my energy in flipping was spent creating lecture video quizzes,
D2L practice quizzes, and in-class practice problems. As such, I wanted
to describe student feedback on these efforts. The graph shown depicts
student responses to the statements &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lecture videos were clear&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The
practice quizzes helped me to understand the course material&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The
practice problems done in-class helped me understand the course
material&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; on course evaluations from Spring 2018 (my first semester
flipping):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/flip-bar.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The
great majority of students strongly agree or agree that the videos are
clear and that the practice quizzes and practice problems are helpful
for understanding course material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will conclude my narrative of the flipping experience with the following excerpt from an email one student sent me at the end of the Fall 2018 semester.  This student suffered from mental health issues that resulted in him missing many class periods.  However, the student did outstanding work on the exams and as a result passed the course with a &amp;ldquo;B&amp;rdquo; grade.  His email in many ways serves a case study of the benefits of the flipped class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Its my first semester back from taking a year off to deal with my mental health but its one that proved to me that I can power through it if I find myself falling into old patterns.  I did miss class throughout various parts of the semester and at times it did feel like I couldn&amp;rsquo;t climb out of the hole when it came to missing the in class quizzes and the in class homework. But with that said, you posting the homework online so I could use it to practice and compare to my classmates work and being able to watch your interactive online lecture on repeat multiple times, watching them before exams, and even the day before quizzes really helped with learning the material even though I wasn&amp;rsquo;t always in class. My math class that I took this semester as well adopted your concept halfway through the semester and it really seemed to help with being able to relook over things multiple times so the concepts would be able to sink in. *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-incorporated-active-learning-in-upper-level-courses&#34;&gt;I incorporated active learning in upper-level courses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My work fostering active learning has not been contained to the
introductory courses! I also put great emphasis in active learning in
upper-level courses such as STAT 310 (Intermediate statistics) and STAT
365 (experimental design and analysis). In STAT 365, a significant
portion of final grade is based on several lab activities which require
students to collect and analyze data and write a report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/oyeuvw6gt7zp1lp/Lab1%20%28Factorial%20CRD%29.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example Lab
1&lt;/a&gt;
| &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/ahie1h0euooll3q/RCBD-activity.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example Lab
2&lt;/a&gt;
| &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/0a5r7sfgblks8lz/Lab%203%20%28Mixed%20model%29.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example Lab
3&lt;/a&gt;
| &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/29dar9rtcxnh7ui/Lab%20FINAL.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example final lab
project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On course evaluations, STAT 365 students rated the labs highly. In
response to the statement &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The labs were useful for understanding the
course material&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 9 responded Strongly Agree, 11 Agree, 2 Disagree,
and 0 Strongly Disagree. Additionally, students often mentioned the labs
as their favorite aspect of the course. Selected responses to the
statement &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The thing I liked MOST about this course was&amp;hellip;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are
shown below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The helicopter lab was definitely my favorite because it was fun to administer and helped me understand what the R code did.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;the labs, specifically the tangram one&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I like the labs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Getting to work with good people on labs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my most recent teaching of STAT 310 (Spring 2018), I dedicated more
in-class time to group work by way of in-class activities. I
administered these activities immediately after discussing a concept.
Accordingly, students were quite new to the concepts covered in the
activities. This gave me a chance to clarify questions and
misunderstandings that might crystalize for students after working
through the activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/0rihivv2iwutt92/Vitruvian%20man%20interactions.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example activity
1&lt;/a&gt;
| &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/txwije7cdht42oy/ANOVA%20group%20work.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example activity
2&lt;/a&gt;
| &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/v3sdx2ihyxr1wyn/Factorial%20Anova%20group%20work.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example activity
3&lt;/a&gt;
| &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/4v7ufv1upxfothb/logistic_transformation.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example activity
4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selected responses from STAT 310 to the statement &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The thing I liked
MOST about this course was&amp;hellip;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are shown below. The responses in
general illustrate that students enjoyed the activities and resulting
discussion surrounding the activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;stat370&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The knowledge of the instructor (brilliant) and the way that the lectures are executed during class. Perfect for my style of learning. Also the music during group work is nice because it helps make the time fly while learning.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I learn stuff and can recall it. I am a finance major and sometimes beta will come up in the discussions in class and I am able to remember what I learned in class.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The activities were a good tool to practice the material in class. Also every day was content dense.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Very fun and everything was organized. The notes provided examples that helped with everything we did.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-taught-stat-370-in-fall-2018&#34;&gt;I taught STAT 370 in Fall 2018&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Spring 2018, I took over duties directing the Statistical Consulting Center.  This included teaching the STAT 370 (Statistical Consulting and Communication).  This course is almost entirely focused on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;active learning&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; as students interact with clients who have &amp;ldquo;real-life&amp;rdquo; statistical research questions they want answered.  I detail this experience from the client side in my &lt;a href=&#34;../crit5/#scc&#34;&gt;Criterion 5 narrative&lt;/a&gt;.  Here, I provide some feedback from the students on their experience in the class.  The following are taken from the Fall 2018 course evaluation in response to the statement  &lt;em&gt;The thing I liked MOST about the course was&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spending time talking with clients and learning communication skills.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interacting with real clients&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The client meetings! They were very good for experience and practicing talking with a client.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Practicing talking to clients and the data manipulation challenges&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The project does help us understand what statisticians do&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Working with clients.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I got to meet real life clients, which was really cool and special since it gave me a feel of the statistics field&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-developed-an-online-version-of-stat-110&#34;&gt;I developed an online version of STAT 110.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work I put into flipping STAT 110 during Spring 2018 paid off in a
big way in my first-ever online course, STAT 110 during Summer Term
2018. All of the online videos I developed during Spring 2018 I employed
again during Summer Term. I improved the videos by including
introductions and summaries capturing my face. I opted for face captures
at the beginning and end of the videos only, as opposed to a
picture-in-picture style wherein my face is displayed throughout the
video. This has the benefit of inducing social learning responses,
without inducing a cognitive load for those who might be distracted by
the PIP method (see e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;http://rene.kizilcec.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/kizilcec2015instructor.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kizilcec et.
Al 2015&lt;/a&gt;). The summer offering similarly included D2L practice quizzes and
weekly graded quizzes, in addition to weekly homework assignments and
two exams. As organization and structure is a critical component of
online courses, I made communication of expectations a priority. Weekly
expectations were outlined via D2L checklists and as announcements on
the D2L homepage. In response to the statement &lt;em&gt;The instructor&amp;rsquo;s
expectations of the student are clear&lt;/em&gt;, 9 Strongly Agreed, 5 Agreed, 2
Disagreed, and 0 Strongly Disagreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students overall rated the course highly. Of 16 responses to the
question &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Which word best describes your overall evaluation of the
course&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 5 rated it &amp;ldquo;Excellent,&amp;rdquo; 9 &amp;ldquo;Good,&amp;rdquo; and 2 &amp;ldquo;Average.&amp;rdquo; Students
also had the following comments on the course:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It was all very clear, and allowed mostly on our own time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lecture videos and organization was good!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The pace is excellent! The second attempt on the quizzes helped me to not stress out.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It was self-paced and there was lots of time to get everything done.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How the schedule is consistent week by week and enough time is provided to complete the homework assignments and quizzes for that week. That was very helpful for the summer time as many students such as myself work full time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I really enjoyed this course&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Overall very well structured!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As online courses gain more prominence (especially during summer term),
I am encouraged by my first offering and convinced that I have developed
a quality online summer course that I will only continue to improve upon
with future iterations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;sec4&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-3&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-mapped-student-learning-outcomes-to-gep-goal-4-criteria&#34;&gt;I mapped student learning outcomes to GEP Goal 4 criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sixth recommendation from the GAISE report is to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;use assessments
to improve and evaluate student learning.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Although this is a
recommendation I strive implement through all my courses, I have put
extra effort into studying the learning of STAT 110 students. One reason
for this exceptional effort is because we offer so many introductory
statistics classes at Winona State. Each semester I usually teach at
least one and sometimes two sections of STAT 110. Accordingly, &amp;ldquo;using
assessments to improve and evaluate student learning&amp;rdquo; bears special
importance for these courses. It is these efforts that I will describe
here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Comprehensive Assessment of
Outcomes in a First Statistics Course (CAOS)
is a rigorously developed test designed to provide an instrument that
would assess students&amp;rsquo; statistical reasoning after any first course in
statistics. Rather than focus on computation and procedures, the CAOS
test focuses on statistical literacy and conceptual understanding, with
a focus on reasoning about variability. The test was developed through a
three-year process of acquiring and writing items, testing and revising
items, and gathering evidence of reliability and validity (delMas, R.,
Garfield, J., Ooms, A., &amp;amp; Chance, B. 2007. &lt;a href=&#34;https://iase-web.org/documents/SERJ/SERJ6(2)_delMas.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Assessing students&amp;rsquo;
conceptual understanding after a first course in statistics.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Statistics
Education Research Journal&lt;/em&gt;, 6(2), 28-58). The CAOS is designed to
assess students&amp;rsquo; conceptual understanding, rather than ability to
memorize facts or formulae, and is therefore very much in line with the
second GAISE recommendation to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;focus on conceptual understanding&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As STAT 110 is GEP Goal 4 courses, starting in Fall 2016, I began using
questions from the CAOS on my final exam, and mapping these questions to
the four Goal 4 competencies. CAOS has national norms as well, so my
intent was to compare performance of my students on each of these Goal 4
areas to national performances on the same questions. Although my final
exam does not consist exclusively of CAOS questions, what I do include
provides a way for me to have some benchmark idea of how my students
should be doing, and how well they actually are doing. The performance
of approximately 300 STAT 110 students on these CAOS questions across
five semesters (Fall 2016; Spring 2017; Fall 2017; Spring 2018; Summer
2018) are shown in the following graph. The height of each bar indicates
percent of my Stat 110 students who answer the question correctly. The
grey error bars indicate 95% confidence intervals for the percent
correct for my students. If the 95% confidence interval does not overlap
the national norm, this indicates that my students are scoring
significantly higher (or lower) than the national norm on that question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/gep.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than a single question from Competency 4, the 95% confidence
interval bars are entirely above or overlap the national norms. This
indicates that on the great majority of these questions, my STAT 110
students perform either significantly better or at the same level as the
national performance on these competencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;sec7&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-4&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-implemented-computational-problem-solving-in-upper-level-statistics-courses&#34;&gt;I implemented computational problem-solving in upper-level statistics courses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommendation 5 from the GAISE report is to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;use technology to
explore concepts and analyze data&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. This recommendation bears merit
from my own experience in graduate school: difficult conceptual ideas
were most often made clear when I was required to accompany a proof or
derivation with a simulation study. Additionally, one of the GAISE&amp;rsquo;s
stated considerations for teachers when selecting technology tools is to
choose one that provides &amp;ldquo;support for reproducible analysis and
integration with word-processing and presentation software&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amstat.org/asa/files/pdfs/GAISE/GaiseCollege_Full.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GAISE
2016&lt;/a&gt;,
p 21). I include some element of computational problem-solving in all my
upper-level statistics courses, but my emphasis has been greatest in
STAT 365 (experimental design and analysis) and STAT 450-460
(mathematical statistics I and II). In these courses, students carry out
computational problem-solving in R, and submit reproducible work by way
of R Markdown. It is these efforts I will here describe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stat-365&#34;&gt;STAT 365&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In STAT 365, I modeled the reproducible framework by producing all my
notes with R Markdown. R Markdown provides a way to seamlessly integrate
text, mathematical symbolism, figures, and computer code and output. See
the handouts on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/courses/stat365/stat365-home/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;most recent STAT 365 course
page&lt;/a&gt; for
examples. Use of this framework allowed me to conduct simulation studies
to illustrate important statistical concepts and provide the code and
output in an integrated format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/rvl1shvc1niiqn5/4_-_CRD_Part1.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example: permutation test for p-values&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/3cjcujwgh4r2aoe/6_-_Treatment_contrasts.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example: standard error&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/1wz7b3aorj0q65o/8_-_power.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example: power&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In homework assignments, students were required to use R to analyze
data, and had the option of submitting their work with R Markdown (some
students exercised this option). Some homework required students to
carry out a simulation study to investigate statistical properties. For
example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/4fma4g90db1dxx2/HW3.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Question 3 of Homework 3, Spring
2017&lt;/a&gt; requires
students to code up a permutation test to simulate a p-value testing for
a difference in group means. On the Spring 2016
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/vsq386txmio4tic/Exam1.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;midterm&lt;/a&gt;,
students had to carry out a simulation study to investigate the effect
of violating the important assumption of equal variance taught in STAT
365. It was very satisfying to finally be able to get students to
investigate &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; we check the &amp;ldquo;equal treatment group variance&amp;rdquo;
assumption, rather than always just telling them to check it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stat-450-460&#34;&gt;STAT 450-460&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;STAT 450-460 is our rigorous statistical theory sequence typically taken
by statistics majors in their senior year. Traditionally, this course is
focused solely on theoretical concepts that require students to be adept
with calculus I-III. This theoretical aptitude is especially important
for students embarking on a graduate degree in statistics. I wanted to
expand upon this traditional theoretical emphasis to include
computational problem-solving. As in STAT 365, all my STAT 450-60 notes
are produced with R Markdown. The result is a collection of high-quality
notes of which I am very proud, which include elements of computation
problem-solving without sacrificing the necessary theoretical rigor of
the sequence. Below are a couple links to some particularly good
examples (in my opinion) of using computational and visual approaches to
solving challenging theoretical problems. Note that the gap-note style provides
space for students to take hand-written notes of more traditional
theoretical (and hence mathematical notation-heavy) concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/196w49gvpyclvgt/Chapter6-transformations.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Handout on distributions of functions of random variables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/8m7v46zjovg52bi/Chapter_8_-_Estimation_and_properties_of_estimators.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Handout on properties of estimators and methods of estimation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/gqroz6bpfhv4bnr/Chapter_16_-_Bayesian_methods.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Handout on Bayesian methods including computational approaches&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My complete set of notes from Stat 450/60 as of the most recent offering
(Fall 2017-Spring 2018) are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/sh/0jztjq0718l8c0n/AADk5hMuQRSi0yuTRBhZmUroa?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;at this
link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to using computational approaches to teaching, I also
designed several homework assignments that required use of the R
statistical computing software to conduct simulation studies and
investigate properties of estimators in cases when analytic approaches
are intractable, or to verify analytic results. These assignments were
in addition to the traditional theoretical assignments out of the course
textbook. Students were required to write these computational
assignments using R Markdown. Below are links to some good examples of
these homework assignments.  The full set of assignment can be viewed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/sh/l3707b9rdao57r0/AAD2MZOWZcYBJoaJ-nNBZTzia?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;following this link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/6wzasmd2clkex6w/Stat450-TakeHomeMidterm-Fall2017-KEY.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Take home midterm from Fall 2017: studying and simulating random variables from non-standard probability density function&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/pl0f8f9x4ab4u2t/Stat450-TakehomeFinal-F18.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Take home final from Fall 2018: developing random number generating algorithm and simulating jointly continuous random variables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/rk59lu4bj9v8hhu/R_HW_Ch9_KEY.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Homework assignment: using simulation studies to compare consistency of mean and median of Cauchy random sample&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/6h473rl1e88v654/R_HW_Ch8_2_KEY.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Homework assignment: using simulation studies to compare actual coverage of nominal 95% exact and asymptotic confidence intervals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/otcbopp456bheyj/R_HW_3_key.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Homework assignment: using the inverse uniform cumulative distribution function approach to simulate random variates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;student-feedback&#34;&gt;Student feedback&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students often commented on student evaluations that they enjoyed the
R-based portions of the course. Below are some statements from
student evaluations from both STAT 365 and STAT 450-60, in response to
the statement &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The thing I like MOST about the course was&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;the r-coding was fun&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The challenging R work&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The opportunity to work in R.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I thought this was a good course. It was my first time using R thoroughly so I felt like I learned a lot.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The R homework. This gave us an opportunity tackle the content with a different perspective than what the book problems taught us.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are responses to the statement &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What did you like most
about the R-based portions of the course?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That R makes math stat life easier!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It helped give a new way of thinking to the content we were learning. If we didn&amp;rsquo;t understand the lecture portion of it then maybe looking at R code would help clear up the confusion. It is also a skill that we will be able to take onto grad school with us.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Using simulations to further cement the examples in the notes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;very helpful for understanding the material better; used real world examples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How it wasn&amp;rsquo;t book work homework. I just like how it gives us something different to do.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everything, I enjoyed learning a new language.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I found the assignments fun because they took into account real world applications.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;sec5&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-5&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-developed-curricula-for-dsci-310-and-taught-its-first-three-offerings&#34;&gt;I developed curricula for DSCI 310 and taught its first three offerings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/courses/dsci310/syllabus/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Syllabus from most recent offering (Fall 2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/courses/dsci310/dsci310-home/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Full Fall 2017 course page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps my proudest accomplishment during my probationary period at
Winona State has been development and teaching of the DSCI 310: Data
Summarization and Visualization course. This course serves as one of the
core requirements of the Data Science major; it is typically the second
Data Science course taken by a DSCI major or minor. I taught this course
three times, in Fall Semesters 2015-2017 (Fall 2015 marking its
first-ever offering at Winona State). Preparing for DSCI 310 was a very
different experience from preparing a traditional statistics course.
I &amp;ldquo;know&amp;rdquo; the routine for preparing a statistics course, in
the sense that some version of the course has been offered before, and I
can usually glean from resources including textbooks, assignments, and
assessments that have been developed previously. I usually have at least
a general idea of what a good final assessment in a statistics course
looks like. Developing DSCI 310 was completely different, as at the time
of development there were very few data visualization courses taught
(although this is rapidly changing), and what was out there could range
from a graduate-level computer science course to a graphic design
course, not necessarily applicable for a student audience of a core, but
semi-introductory, data science course. Even developing the assessments
for DSCI 310 was a challenge, and has evolved over the past three years:
how does one evaluate a data visualization as &amp;ldquo;high quality&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;poor
quality&amp;rdquo;? For that matter, what exactly IS a data visualization?! These
are the questions on which I spent a great deal of time reflecting and
researching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, I learned as much as the students as I researched this
course. In preparing for the course, I learned about and drew heavily
from the visualization research of Ed Tufte, William S. Cleveland,
Leland Wilkinson, and Hadley Wickham. In its most recent offering, the
course content was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is a data visualization?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding the elementary perceptual tasks (EPT)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visualization best principles and practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Univariate visualizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multivariate visualizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3-way scatterplots and maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interactive dashboards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data visualization in R with ggplot2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to visualization concepts and best practices, I also learned
a lot about state-of-the-art visualization tools. I became fluent with
Tableau and the R package ggplot2, two of the most prominent data
visualization tools. Students coming out of the course were also fluent
in at least one of these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary assessments in the course consisted of the following. Note
that since the point of a data visualization is to communicate insight,
an important aspect of the course was oral presentations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;design-tasks&#34;&gt;Design tasks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students were required to complete various &amp;ldquo;design tasks&amp;rdquo; throughout the
semester, where I provided a data set and set of questions that students
had to answer visually. The students then critiqued several of their
peers&amp;rsquo; visualizations using CrowdGrader and had a chance to incorporate
peer feedback before submitting a final version to me for grading. See
the &lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/courses/dsci310/dsci310-home/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;course
webpage&lt;/a&gt; for
some example design tasks. The peer evaluation component was a critical
one, as it afforded students the chance to flex their critiquing muscles
and glean ideas from other students (my own best data visualizations are
a collection of techniques I&amp;rsquo;ve seen in other visualizations I like!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;midterm-project&#34;&gt;Midterm project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The midterm project required students to work in groups to create an
oral presentation that they gave in class. I assigned the data set and a
set of preliminary questions. The groups then prepared a visualization
presentation and presented their projects to the entire class. Grades
for the midterm project were assigned on the quality of the data
visualizations (50%), oral presentation (30%), and group member
evaluation (20%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/courses/dsci310/midterm/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example midterm project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-project&#34;&gt;Final project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DSCI 310 culminated with a final project that was a substantial part of
students&amp;rsquo; final grades. For the final project, students had to find
their own data set of interest and create a set of visualization
dashboards. The final project gave students the chance to encounter the
entire data cycle: from identifying a data source, to data &amp;ldquo;wrangling&amp;rdquo;
(cleaning, transforming), to visualizing key insights. Each student gave
an oral presentation of their visualization dashboards to the entire
class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/courses/dsci310/final/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example final project, including links to student final data visualizations (click student name to view student&amp;rsquo;s final project)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students&amp;rsquo; work on all projects was evaluated with a rubric. As my own
understanding of what makes a high-quality data visualization evolved,
so too did my rubric! Below, you can compare the Fall 2015 rubric with
the Fall 2017 rubric. Note the increased granularity of the Fall 2017
rubric. The evolution of these rubrics resulted from me evaluating
student visualizations, finding myself annoyed by certain aspects, and
having to carefully ask myself &amp;ldquo;what exactly is lacking in this
visualization?&amp;rdquo; As such, I have greatly improved in my own ability to
specify my expectations and communicate what aspects I look for in
high-quality data visualizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/23xp5bpi74rzhil/Fall%202015%20Description.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Fall 2015 final
rubric&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/6seigmxr2f3pef6/Fall%202017%20Rubric.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Fall 2017 final
rubric&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;student-outcomes-and-evaluation&#34;&gt;Student outcomes and evaluation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;dsci310&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most gratifying aspects of teaching DSCI 310 is the immediate
and apparent impact of the course on student success even prior to
graduation. Along with the positive student evaluations below, recent
success of DSCI 310 students in data analysis competitions has been due
in part to their ability to communicate data insights effectively and
visually. Some of these successes include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 2018&lt;/strong&gt;: 3 separate Winona State teams won &amp;ldquo;Best Overall Presentation,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Acumen Award&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;Honorable Mention&amp;rdquo; at MinneMUDAC 2017 out of more than 60 teams. &lt;a href=&#34;http://minneanalytics.org/more-than-60-teams-present-findings-at-minnemudac-2017/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Press release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 2017&lt;/strong&gt;:  As part of their midterm project in DSCI 310 (Fall 2017), groups
    of students participated in the nationwide, ASA-sponsored Police
    Data Challenge. All groups had to visualize a data set with
    millions of 911 emergency calls in Seattle, WA and submit a
    presentation. One of these groups from DSCI 310 (Fall 2017) won
    &amp;ldquo;Best Overall College&amp;rdquo; presentation and presented their findings
    to the Police Foundation. &lt;a href=&#34;http://thisisstatistics.org/police-data-challenge-congratulations-to-our-winners/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Press
        Release&lt;/a&gt; |  &lt;a href=&#34;http://thisisstatistics.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/Best-Overall-College-.pptx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Winning
        presentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 2017&lt;/strong&gt;: A team of Winona State students won First Place Overall at
    MUDAC 2018. Another WSU team was one of the final 5 teams. &lt;a href=&#34;http://wsumathstats.blogspot.com/2018/04/mudac-2018.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Press
        release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring 2017&lt;/strong&gt;:  Winona State team wins Best Overall Analysis at MUDAC 2017.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fall 2016&lt;/strong&gt;: Winona State team wins Serendipitous Discovery Award at MinneMUDAC 2016. &lt;a href=&#34;http://minneanalytics.org/diving-into-water-data-the-outcomes-of-minnemudac/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Press
        release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are some email excerpts from students, received after graduating
from WSU, expressing how much they valued the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dear Prof. Bergen,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Greetings from Iowa! I am Tylar and hopefully you still remember who I
am. I graduated from WSU last summer and became a graduate student at
UIowa now. I love data visualization and I loved your DSCI310 class at
WSU.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dear Dr. Bergen,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I want to thank you for your help, and advice while I was writing my
senior project. In particular your emphasis on creating infographics
that quickly and clearly communicate information has been very
important. Had I not been asked to focus on graphics in the Data
Visualizations class, an while working on my senior paper I feel that I
would be missing an important piece of effective communication. Thank
you for the work that you put in, and the time you took to help me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;From a student interning at Merchants Bank&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I just wanted to say thank you for all the skills you have taught me in
data visualization! They have come so handy here! Even though we don&amp;rsquo;t
use Tableau here, I&amp;rsquo;m still able to use the fundamentals about data
viz you have taught me in class! Thank you so much for that! Honestly,
if you were looking for people to write testimonies on your website on
how amazing you are at data viz and at teaching DSCI 310, I&amp;rsquo;m be the
first to do so haha. Thank you so much again for everything!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figures below show student responses from end-of-semester course
evaluations aggregated across all 3 semesters of DSCI 310. The responses
are to three statements: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have improved in my ability to effectively
critique data visualizations;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have improved in my ability to
effectively visualize data&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Which word best describes your
overall evaluation of the course?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Specifically, students tended to
strongly agree or agree that they improved in their ability to
effectively critique visualizations and effectively visualize data. In
the most recent Fall 2017 and Fall 2016 offerings, 100% of students
rated the course as &amp;ldquo;Excellent&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Good.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/viz-critique-create.jpg&#34; width=&#34;850&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/viz-eval.png&#34; width=&#34;350&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see visualizations created by DSCI 310 students for their final
projects for all three semesters, as well as a selection of data
visualizations used for in-class projects, please view my &lt;a href=&#34;https://public.tableau.com/profile/silas.bergen#!/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tableau
Public profile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;sec6&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-6&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-was-a-motivating-passionate-and-helpful-instructor-in-all-my-courses&#34;&gt;I was a motivating, passionate, and helpful instructor in all my courses.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teaching is a whole-person responsibility. Yes, I am responsible for helping
students learn statistical content and teaching them how to be effective
data analysts and communicators. But more importantly, I am tasked
with the responsibility and privilege of accompanying them in an
important stage of their personal growth. Above and beyond simply
ensuring they meet learning outcomes, I want my students to trust me and
to enjoy learning from me, and to know that I am always available to
help and capable of helping if they struggle. Only then can I fully
mentor my students, be they a nursing student in STAT 110 terrified of
math or a rock-star mathematician breezing through our statistics
curricula with straight-A&amp;rsquo;s. Ultimately, this relationship influences my
effectiveness in helping students achieve the original goal of meeting
learning objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below, I provide evidence of creating an effective and productive
learning environment by way of student and colleague feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;student-feedback-1&#34;&gt;Student feedback&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To determine whether I am meeting these goals, I ask students across all
my courses whether they strongly agree, agree, disagree, or strongly
disagree with the following statements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The instructor exhibits a genuine enthusiasm and enjoys teaching the
course.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The instructor has a thorough knowledge and understanding of the
subject matter.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The instructor is willing/able to provide help inside and outside of
class.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The instructor presents the material in a clear manner.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The instructor&amp;rsquo;s expectations of the students are clear&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure below shows updated responses from all classes I have taught through &lt;strong&gt;Fall 2018&lt;/strong&gt;; there
are a total of &lt;strong&gt;753&lt;/strong&gt; student responses shown&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/prof-rate2.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the responses have been very positive, especially with respect
to my enthusiasm, knowledge of material, and helpfulness. Of the five
questions, these are the ones I am most concerned with and am
accordingly gratified to receive such high evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next plot shows student responses to the question &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Which word best
describes your overall evaluation of the instructor&amp;rsquo;s teaching?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, once again aggregating responses across all classes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/prof-overall-F18.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the &lt;strong&gt;753&lt;/strong&gt; responses, 659/753 = 88% used either &amp;ldquo;excellent&amp;rdquo; or
&amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; to describe their overall evaluation of my teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Displayed below are some comments from students taken across all year&amp;rsquo;s course evaluations, in response to the question &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The thing I liked MOST about this course was&amp;hellip;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you are seeing this Dr. Bergen, you are a great teacher and you make coming to class fun.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Silas is a really great professor.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;He makes the course enjoyable and easy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The professor was very approachable and wanted everyone to succeed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;the enthusiasm that Silas had!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your attitude as a professor- you are easy to talk to and ask questions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Professor Bergen is a really good teacher.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dr. Bergen&amp;rsquo;s enthusiam. He was easy to understand and very approachable with any questions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I could tell the teacher absolutely loves teaching the class and knew how to incroporate fun and humor into it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How understanding and helpful Professor Bergen was. Also he listened to some of what students wanted out of the class.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You did an excellent job as a professor. It is clear you cared about the material, and more importantly, about each students success. Thank you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;the instructor&amp;rsquo;s genuine love for the topic and the students&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How friendly and willing to help our professor was. I really didn&amp;rsquo;t think I would like stats but I didn&amp;rsquo;t dread going to class everyday.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The teacher (I swear I&amp;rsquo;m not sucking up)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The instructor was kind, engaging, and seemed knowledgeable about the topic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It was an open learning environment with an instructor that cared.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bergen as a person. A great guy and saying he is willing to help any one of his students is an understatement. He wants you to do well which is a great feeling and helps a lot.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The examples the professor gave in class to go with the lectures were real-life examples that helped me understand the topic better. And, if anyone had a question as we were going through the power point, he was always more than willing to answer it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The availability of the professor outside of class to help. He never makes you feel like any question is ridiculous, and is super patient. You can truly tell that he genuinely enjoys the subject and wants his students to succeed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Silas presented the material in a way that is easy to understand and offers great help during office hours&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lectures were not boring and Silas makes the class fun every day.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Silas&amp;rsquo; positive attitude and willingness to help&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;the professor was very good at explaining things and made sure that everyone understood before moving on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;great professor with a good personality cares for the students&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It was very interesting and the professor kept us all intrigued by providing interesting examples to practice with&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Professor Bergen. I&amp;rsquo;ve always hated math and he allowed me to enjoy it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I liked the enthusiasm of the instructor and the examples really helped me to understand the information.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The knowledge of the instructor (brilliant) and the way that the lectures are executed during class.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are always open for students to come in during open office hours to help, and try explaining things your best when we ask questions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Professor was very helpful and clear, I feel that I learned and understood a lot compared to normal math classes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Professor&amp;rsquo;s enthusiasm and genuine interest in the subject, and the humor.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Being able to ask the professor any questions without judgement&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Articulate, coherent, knowledgable professor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The professor was always willing to help. Never made me feel like I was asking a stupid question.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;teacher was very enjoyable and it was fun to come to class&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Professor Bergen is a good teacher and very helpful. He is diverse in his teaching abilities and is helpful to most students from what I percieved.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I finally understood what was being taught because the professor did a good job at teaching it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following are excerpts from emails I have received from students. While
the comments from end-of-course student evaluations are valuable, I find
these emails especially valuable, as they are unprompted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dr. Bergen,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With my work schedule, yesterday and today, I will not have time for
the extra credit assignment, but here is the page from the end of the
survey. You did an excellent job teaching the course. Your interest in
helping your students is terrific.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Silas,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It was refreshing to take a class from you (even when repeated). I
wanted to thank you for your investment in teaching statistics. This
course was very beneficial to my education at WSU.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hello Dr. Bergen,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is my new email address at the University of Iowa. I was trying to
forward you this but kept forgetting it over time. The only thing that I
would like to mention here is that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t love your Stat 450/460
homework more. Every class (3 in total) I am taking now has weekly or
biweekly homework due, and it is hard like hell. So far I have written,
either on Latex or by hand, more than 10 pages for each homework. The
length is comparable to your stat homework. Many thanks to your
homework! Although it didn&amp;rsquo;t prepare for the topics in math, it was
really a good start of cultivating tenacity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hi Professor Silas,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I wanted to say thank you so much for helping me out yesterday. I was
so overwhelmed by everything that was going on. I really appreciate your
compassion and helping me through it. I&amp;rsquo;m going to take your advise and
relax more. Thank you much again and I&amp;rsquo;m really, really thankful to
have you as my adviser.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Silas,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Just getting home from hanging out with a few buddies from back home
and reality hit me. I just wanted to let you know how much I loved you
as a teacher. You&amp;rsquo;re seriously the sincerest professor I ever had the
privilege of learning from throughout my 5 years at the university. I
know I probably tested your limits from time to time, but I really want
to express my gratitude for what you taught me over the numerous courses
I had with you. These are things I will carry with me forever. Even
though I wasn&amp;rsquo;t in class that much this last year as I tried to get my
life figured out, I hope you enjoyed having me as a student.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hopefully I run into you sometime down road. Now that officially
tomorrow(today) we are both alumni, give me a call if you ever want to
meet to watch a ball game or something or grab a cold one. I just want
to wish you and your family the best on your future and wherever it may
take you. I admire you very much and I&amp;rsquo;m indebted to you. God bless.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hi Dr. Bergen,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My name is Binnan Yu, I am your former student, had your statistics 2 years ago at WSU. I am a Phd student in rehabilitation medicine at University of Washington Seattle right now.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I am sending this email to express my gratitude for your great teaching. My research at UW is clinic biomechanics, but everyone have to take 3 biostats course since the Phd program is under school of medicine. Somehow I found the professor at UW is unclear about many topics so I have to review the notes you used 2 years ago at WSU, and found it extremely helpful, and also the Statkey you used a lot in class for simulation.   Thanks for your great teaching and hope everything goes well at Winona.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Best Regards&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;colleague-feedback&#34;&gt;Colleague feedback&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked my colleagues Tisha Hooks and Chris Malone to visit my classroom
and provide feedback on my teaching. I am including their feedback here.
Excerpted text is below; full text from their reviews are available by
following the provided links. I believe these comments provide evidence
not only of my current level of teaching excellence, but also my
eagerness to improve. The latter trait especially will serve me well as
I continue to grow as an educator for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/gb1s2s8ytcwyinv/hooks-comments.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tisha&amp;rsquo;s
comments&lt;/a&gt;
on my 2015-2016 PDR:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Silas is excelling in his role as an educator. I am continually
impressed by the amount of work he puts into his teaching, his
willingness to help students, and his passion for both teaching and
learning. In only his first two years, he has made invaluable
contributions by creating new and improving existing curriculum. Even
when given course materials from others, he works hard to put his own
spin on the material and to make it better. had the opportunity to
observe Silas as he taught STAT 110 this past spring, and I am very glad
that I did. I witnessed a relaxed, yet productive, learning atmosphere.
He addressed students by name, and no one seemed afraid to ask
questions. On one occasion, after answering a student&amp;rsquo;s question, Silas
asked, &amp;ldquo;Does that make sense?&amp;rdquo; The student nodded her head yes, but
Silas recognized that she was still confused. So, he tried explaining
things in a different way until it was clear that she (and others) did
understand. His ability to detect her confusion and to address it in a
way that didn&amp;rsquo;t really single her out is, to me, an important quality
for a teacher to possess. I also commend Silas for incorporating Top Hat
into his course. His use of Top Hat during this particular class period
was excellent. He used the questions to address misconceptions, and he
led a good discussion after each question regarding why the wrong
answers were wrong and why the right answer was right. The questions
seemed to be asked at perfect intervals, material was introduced at what
seemed to be a perfect pace, and the Top Hat questions really did draw
students into the classroom. I sat in the back of the lecture hall and
could see most computer screens. Almost every single screen I saw was
displaying his notes, and students seemed to follow along the entire 50
minutes. I wish I could say that the participation rate was as high in
my own classes! I took notes on his teaching the day that I observed his
STAT 110, and my last comment says, &amp;ldquo;I learned from watching Silas
teach.&amp;rdquo; As I watched him and after I left, I kept thinking about things
I could do to improve my own courses.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/qdqhkju0gqyis8p/tisha_comments.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tisha&amp;rsquo;s
comments&lt;/a&gt;
on my 2016-2017 PDR:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Silas has consistently demonstrated teaching excellence. He is caring,
enthusiastic, and patient. He presents statistical ideas to students in
a clear, thoughtful manner. Finally, he challenges his students (but
also makes it known that he is there to help them learn). Silas&amp;rsquo;s
documentation in this year&amp;rsquo;s PDR clearly provides evidence of his
teaching effectiveness. His student evaluations are excellent, his
reflection on the past and efforts to improve are sincere, and his
examples of lecture notes/learning opportunities are exemplary. He has
most certainly provided valuable contributions to our statistics and
data science curricula.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I had the opportunity to observe Silas teaching a STAT 365 course this
spring&amp;hellip;.  I thoroughly enjoyed sitting in on this class. It is obvious that he
puts a great deal of time and effort into his course materials, and the
end result is excellent. As always, I was impressed with what I
observed, and I walked away from Silas&amp;rsquo; class with ideas for improving
my own teaching.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/hj8mp0ak36j1cme/chris_comments.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Chris&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;
comments on my 2016-2017 PDR:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have witnessed substantial growth in Silas as an educator. Silas did
not have much teaching experience before coming to WSU. He continues to
improve each semester by tweaking his delivery methods, incorporating a
balance of individual/group work, etc. I have visited Silas&amp;rsquo;s classroom
in Spring 2016 and Spring 2017 and I noticed that he appears more
comfortable and natural in the classroom this year compared to last. The
classroom environment he creates for students is fruitful for learning.
His report mentions the use of a partially flipped approach in STAT 110
and I would encourage Silas to continue to tweak his deliver -less
formal lecture and more interaction with students and amongst students
the better.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Silas taught the Math-Stat sequence for us this year. My understanding
is that this course went well for him and the students. This course
takes a substantial amount of preparation -much more than a typical
course and especially considering he took the time to put the course
notes into a R Markdown format. The rest of us faculty members will
certainly reap the benefits of his work when teaching this course.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Overall, Silas continues to grow as an educator, which is of utmost
importance for a path to tenure regarding Criteria I.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concludes my narrative in support of Criterion I: Evidence of Teaching Effectiveness.  I hope and believe that my narrative not only demonstrates that I have satisfied this criterion, but also provides evidence that I will only stive to continue to grow and improve as an educator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criterion 2: Scholarship and Creative Achievement</title>
      <link>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit2/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the following narrative will demonstrate, the focus of my scholarship and creative achievement has evolved over the course of my probationary period.  Early on, I was focused on finshing up and publishing some of my PhD research on measurement error correction methods in air pollution epidemiology studies. This resulted in several conventional peer-reviewed articles in well-reputed journals. After finding closure in that line of research, my interests turned to data visualization as I was deeply immersed in developing DSCI 310: data summarization and visualization. There has turned to be a great deal of interest among the statistics education community in data visualization both in general and as an undergraduate course. Accordingly much of my creative achievement the past several years has centered on giving presentations and workshops at national and international conferences on what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned during the course of creating DSCI 310.  Most recently I assumed the responsibility of directing the Statistical Consulting Center and have prepared and published some peer-reviewed manuscripts as a result of these collaborations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My narrative for Criterion 2 is organized into the following three categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#articles&#34;&gt;Peer-reviewed journal publications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#presentations&#34;&gt;Conference presentations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#workshops&#34;&gt;Workshops&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;articles&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;peer-reviewed-journal-publications&#34;&gt;Peer-reviewed journal publications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34;&gt; Back to top &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-author-articles-air-pollution-epidemiology&#34;&gt;First-author articles: air pollution epidemiology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These articles disseminate the methods I developed to correct for measurement error in air pollution epidemiology studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt;, Sheppard L, Kaufman JD, and Szpiro AA.  Multipollutant measurement error in air pollution epidemiology studies arising from predicting exposures with penalized regression splines.  &lt;em&gt;Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series C &amp;ndash; Applied Statistics.&lt;/em&gt;  65(5):731-753.  2016. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5076926/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to article.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt; and Szpiro AA.  Mitigating the impact of measurement error when using penalized regression to model exposure in two-stage air pollution epidemiology studies.  &lt;em&gt;Environmental and Ecological Statistics&lt;/em&gt;.  22(3):601-631.  2015. &lt;a href=&#34;https://link-springer-com.wsuproxy.mnpals.net/article/10.1007/s10651-015-0314-y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to online published version&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/48hsp7vw4djwvmr/BergenSzpiroEES.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Full-text link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;co-authored-articles-air-pollution-epidemiology&#34;&gt;Co-authored articles: air pollution epidemiology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also co-authored some articles in which my methods for predicting air pollution exposure and correcting for subsequent measurement error were applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim S-Y, Sheppard L, &lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt;, Szpiro AA, Sampson PD, Kaufman JD, and Vedal S.  Prediction of fine particulate matter chemical components with a spatio-temporal model for the Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis cohort.  &lt;em&gt;Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology.&lt;/em&gt;  26:520-528.  2016.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/jes201629&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to article.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chan SH, Van Hee VC, &lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt;, Szpiro AA, DeRoo LA, London SJ,
Marshall JD, Kaufman JD, and Sandler DP. Long-term air pollution
exposure and blood pressure in the Sister Study.  &lt;em&gt;Environmental Health Perspectives.&lt;/em&gt;
123(10):951-958.  2015.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www-ncbi-nlm-nih-gov.wsuproxy.mnpals.net/pmc/articles/PMC4590742/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to article.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim S-Y, Sheppard L, Kaufman JD, &lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt;, Szpiro AA, Larson TV,
Adar SD, Diez Roux AV, Polak JF, and Vedal S. Individual-level
concentrations of fine particulate matter chemical components and
subclinical atherosclerosis: A cross-sectional analysis based on two
advanced exposure prediction models in the Multi-Ethnic Study of
Atherosclerosis. &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Epidemiology&lt;/em&gt;.  180(7):718-728.  2014.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic-oup-com.wsuproxy.mnpals.net/aje/article/180/7/718/149800&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to article.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;co-authored-articles-collaboration-through-statistical-consulting-center&#34;&gt;Co-authored articles: collaboration through Statistical Consulting Center&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Selvaratnam ND, Hettiarachchi D, Dantanarayana ND, &lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt;, Ponnamperuma L,  and Selvaratnam S. Investigating the psychometric properties, and IRT analysis of the Sinhala generalized self-efficacy scale (S-GSES). &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Multidisciplinary Research.&lt;/em&gt; 4(2): 73-95. 2018.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/326423087_Investigating_the_psychometric_properties_and_IRT_analysis_of_the_Sinhala_generalized_self-efficacy_scale_S-GSES&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to article.&lt;/a&gt;  (My work on this article was particularly interesting to me, as I had to learn Item Response Theory (IRT), a commonly-used analysis method in the psychometrics field. Up to this point I had never heard of IRT.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fye HJ, &lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt;, and Baltrinic ER.  The relationships between ASCA National Model implementation, supervision satisfaction, and school counselor burnout.  Submitted to &lt;em&gt;Journal of Counseling and Development&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Snyder K, Paulson P, and &lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt;.  A Website Assessment Tool for Patient Engagement: A Verification.  Submitted to &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Healthcare Management&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;presentations&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-1&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conference-presentations&#34;&gt;Conference presentations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;presentations-resulting-from-advising-student-work&#34;&gt;Presentations resulting from advising student work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following presentations at JSM 2017 derived from work with the WINSTATS REU, which I describe in greater detail in my Criterion 4 narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kallis A, Aadland M, and &lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;em&gt;Interactive dashboard: using census microdata to map population characteristics.&lt;/em&gt;  Joint Statistical Meetings.  Baltimore, MD.  2017.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/files/JSM_Poster_Presentation.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to poster.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Malone C, &lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt;, and Deppa B.  &lt;em&gt;ASA REU Experiences at Winona State University.&lt;/em&gt;  Joint Statistical Meetings.  Baltimore, MD.  2017. &lt;a href=&#34;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/jsm/2017/onlineprogram/AbstractDetails.cfm?abstractid=323913&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to abstract and presentation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tourangeau E, Halbleib J, and &lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;em&gt;A universal measure of household weath from global census microdata.&lt;/em&gt;   Joint Statistical Meetings.  Baltimore, MD.  2017.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/files/JSM-Poster.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to poster.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;presentations-disseminating-creative-achievement-in-my-courses&#34;&gt;Presentations disseminating creative achievement in my courses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following presentations, I disseminated my work developing DSCI 310.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;em&gt;A data visualization course for undergraduate data science students&lt;/em&gt;.  CAUSE webinar.  December 2016. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.causeweb.org/cause/webinar/teaching/2016-12&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to recording.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is an email from the webinar organizer regarding my presentation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img//cause-email.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;em&gt;A data visualization course for undergraduate data science students&lt;/em&gt;.  Joint Statistical Meetings.  Chicago, IL.  August 2016. &lt;a href=&#34;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/jsm/2016/onlineprogram/AbstractDetails.cfm?abstractid=319054&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to presentation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The table below shows the results of audience evaluations of my presentation.  All but 1 of the 20 evaluations rated the overall presentation as &amp;ldquo;Above average&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;one&amp;rdquo; of the &amp;ldquo;best&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img//jsm-eval.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presentations below described my work incorporating data-based social justice themes in my introductory statistics courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;em&gt;Melding data with social justice in undergraduate statistics and data science courses.&lt;/em&gt;  Promoting Understanding of Statistics about Society.  International Association for Statistical Education Roundtable Conference.  Berlin, Germany.  July 2016.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://iase-web.org/documents/papers/rt2016/Bergen.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to published proceeding.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bergen S&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Talking social justice in intro stats&lt;/em&gt;.  Joint Statistical Meetings.  Seattle, WA.  August 2015.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/4q16p7w6otj8aah/Talking%20social%20justice.pptx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to presentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;workshops&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-2&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;workshops&#34;&gt;Workshops&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with some of my statistics and data science colleagues at Winona State, I have co-led several workshops primarily on teaching data science and visualization principles and concepts.  I have especially enjoyed leading these workshops.
They facilitate the opportunity to interact with participants more than a traditional conference presentation, while still enabling us to share teaching methodology and curricula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data visualization: principles and practice using Tableau Public and Python.&lt;/em&gt;  Todd Iverson, co-organizer.  International Conference on Teaching Statistics.  Kyoto, Japan.  July 2018.  Half-day workshop   (&lt;a href=&#34;https://icots.info/10/?workshop=E&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to abstract&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/WSU-DataScience/ICOTS10_Data_Visualization&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to materials&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Software carpentry.&lt;/em&gt; With Hannah Leverentz, Chris Malone, Nathan Moore, Todd Iverson, and Chris Phan.  Winona State University. August 14-16, 2017.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://ntmoore.github.io/2017-08-14-winona/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to workshop page.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A trip through the data cycle: webscraping and data visualization with Python and Tableau.&lt;/em&gt;  Todd Iverson, co-organizer.  U.S. Conference on Teaching Statistics.  May 2017.  (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/wsu-stat489/USCOTS2017_workshop&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to workshop materials.&lt;/a&gt;)  This 2-day workshop proposal was reviewed by conference organizers and our abstract was accepted.  We were invited to lead a 2-day workshop on web scraping and data visualization.  The email below is from one of the workshop participants (click image for larger view).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;../../img/uscots-email.PNG&#39;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img//uscots-email.PNG&#34; width=&#34;1600&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teaching data science.&lt;/em&gt; Chris Malone, co-organizer.  U.S. Conference on Teaching Statistics.  May 2015. &lt;a href=&#34;http://course1.winona.edu/cmalone/workshops/uscots2015/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link to workshop materials.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criterion 3: Continuing preparation and study</title>
      <link>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit3/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have learned so much during my probationary period at Winona State!  One of the aspects of my job for which I am so grateful is the daily opportunity to learn.  &amp;ldquo;Boredom&amp;rdquo; is unfortunately a common companion for many people at their work; I am so gratified to say I am not one of these people.  In the following narrative I will provide evidence of ways in which I have continued to learn and grow as a professional in my field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I reflected on the professional development activities I undertook during my probationary period, I was struck by how things that I learned during my early years have become mainstays of my current professional practice.  Accordingly I have decided to organize this narrative chronologically: each of the following sections is an academic year.  My intent here is not merely to list the articles I have read or the conferences I attended over the years, but to give specific examples of ways the preparation and study I undertook influenced my practice to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2014-2015&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015-2016&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016-2017&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2017-2018&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2014-2015&#34;&gt;2014-2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study and preparation in which I engaged in 2014-2015 included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning the R Markdown environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading the following articles on success (or lack thereof) of the flipped statistics classroom:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Winquist JR and Carlson KA. Flipped classroom results: better performance than lecture over one year later. Journal of Statistical Education. Volume 22, Number 3. 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gundlach E, Richards KAR, Nelson D, and Levesque-Bristol C.  A comparison of attitudes, statistical reasoning, performance, and perceptions for web-augmented traditional, fully online, and flipped sections of a statistical literacy class.  Journal of Statistical Education. Volume 23, Number 1.  2015.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;learning-the-r-markdown-environment&#34;&gt;Learning the R Markdown environment&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my 2014-15 PDR, I wrote the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was very excited to finally learn R Markdown this past year.  R Markdown is a functionality within R Studio, and is a way to very nicely reproduce R code and output within the body of a document.  I had heard about R Markdown in graduate school, but never made time to learn it.  This year I intended to use R in STAT 310 and so finally got down to learning R Markdown as a way of teaching R to my students. Using R Markdown, I made a document introducing R to my STAT 310 students and walking them through the R commands necessary to complete a Homework problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is striking in reading this that at one point I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; use R Markdown!  I use it almost daily now: from preparing course notes to writing reports for statistical consulting clients.  R Markdown is so prominently featured in statistical report writing that I have made it an integral part of the writing component of the STAT 450/460 sequence, which is a writing intensive.  See the relevant section from the &lt;a href=&#34;../crit1/#sec7&#34;&gt;Criterion 1 narrative&lt;/a&gt; for examples of R Markdown use in Stat 450/460.  Some more recent examples from this course, as well as examples of statistical consulting reports developed using R Markdown, are provided below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;STAT 450 assignments requiring use of R Markdown (Fall 2018)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/scj6w5tyxug2odq/HW1_KEY.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example 1: Key to HW assignment 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/httefljmt9sxuc6/HW2-KEY.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example 2: Key to HW assignment 2; note blend of mathematical notation, R code, and computer graphics characteristic of a document rendered with R Markdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Statistical consulting reports developed with R Markdown&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/022db5g976pmhbb/Report_for_K_Snyder.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example 1: Report for Kim Snyder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/usxomrql6poxzz4/Report.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example 2: Report for Sara Nelson and Jessica Roslansky&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;studying-the-literature-on-flipped-classrooms&#34;&gt;Studying the literature on flipped classrooms&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As early as my first year I was already considering the flipped classroom model, wherein students learn the content outside class and spend the in-class time problem-solving and applying the course material.  In 2014-2015 I was already laying the groundwork towards flipping, and reading articles that studied the merits of flipping.  I gradually began to flip the STAT 110 classroom; efforts that I have &lt;a href=&#34;../crit1/#flipit&#34;&gt;described in much more detail in my Criterion 1 narrative&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2015-2016&#34;&gt;2015-2016&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My highlights from the 2015-2016 period included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning software tools &lt;a href=&#34;https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://dplyr.tidyverse.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning data visualization software Tableau&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attending impactful talks at professional conferences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My primary professional development in 2015-2016 involved learning software that is central to much of the data science curricula we now teach.  Specifically, I solidified my understanding of the &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; tools &lt;a href=&#34;https://dplyr.tidyverse.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and the Tableau software package.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://dplyr.tidyverse.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a data wrangling package and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a data visualization package; I use both extensively both in my own practice and &lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/courses/dsci310/ipums-visualization-ggplot/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;in my&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/courses/dsci310/ipums-visualization-key/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;courses&lt;/a&gt;.  Learning Tableau for the first time was fundamental as part of teaching the DSCI 310 course for the first time in Fall 2015.  See &lt;a href=&#34;https://public.tableau.com/profile/silas.bergen#!/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my Tableau Public profile&lt;/a&gt; for a sampling of the data visualizations I and my students have created with Tableau.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was August 2015 that I heard a talk by Dennis Sun at the Joint Statistical Meetings on student peer evaluation in statistics courses.  I have described this experience &lt;a href=&#34;../crit1/#crowdgrader&#34;&gt;in more detail in my Criterion 1 narrative&lt;/a&gt;.  I consider this experience and what I learned from it an instrumental part of my professional development during academic year 2015-16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2016-2017&#34;&gt;2016-2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Highlights from 2016-2017 included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attending the IASE roundtable Promoting understanding of statistics about society in July 2016&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attending Todd Iverson&amp;rsquo;s Special Topics Python course for part of Spring Semester 2017&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The International Association of Statistics Education (IASE) roundtable I attended in Berlin, Germany was an especially unique and positive experience.  It was fantastic to be exposed to the approaches and methods taken by statistical educators from around the world.  Over dinner and drinks, we would dialogue about the different challenges faced in different environments.  As the roundtable theme was on promoting understanding of statistics about society, we had many conversations about how crucial statistics are in the current socio-political climate, from Brexit to Donald Trump to the alt-right movement in Germany and across Europe and the U.S.  At this roundtable, I met and developed a collaboration with Lara Cleveland from the International Public Use Microdata Series-International (IPUMS-I).  Ironically, Lara is based in the Twin Cities metro area, but we never met until gathering in Berlin.  Leveraging this connection, my colleagues and I wrote an application to the American Statistical Association to bring 4 undergraduates from across the United States to Winona State for a 10-week research experience for undergraduates (REU) for Summer 2017.  This experience is &lt;a href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;described in more detail in my Criterion 4 narrative&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python is rapidly becoming an industry standard for data science, and I was eager to learn about its functionality by sitting in on Todd&amp;rsquo;s DSCI 489: Special Topics class this semester.  While I had to stop attending midway through as the semester grew busy, what I was able to attend was extremely beneficial.  It definitely scratched the itch I had to be exposed to and learn some Python.  I even &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/gauofewem1huo9n/HW4-code.py?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;completed an entire homework assignment&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2017-2018&#34;&gt;2017-2018&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this year I continuted to teach myself software tools, most prominently &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;, an open-source website building tool.  I used this tool to build a &lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;new personal website&lt;/a&gt; where I could host course materials and the occasional blog post (I consider it a &amp;ldquo;professional diary&amp;rdquo; of sorts), as well as the website you are currently using to read this portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criterion 4: Contributions to student growth and development</title>
      <link>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit4/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the five criterion narratives, this the one I have most been looking forward to writing.  In many ways, my desire to invest in a career centered around teaching was (and is) fueled by an excitement about making a significant and positive difference in the lives of students during a formative period of their life&amp;rsquo;s arc.  Much of this happens in the classroom, but there is so much that takes place outside the classroom walls: in my office, in a van on the way to a field trip, over a celebratory beer at the final semester&amp;rsquo;s end, in the time spend crafting a letter on whose wings the recipient wiltoward graduate school.  To the students I have had the pleasure of shaping in some way, and who have left their indelible mark on me, I dedicate this narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;outline&#34;&gt;Outline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following are the primary categories of ways I have contributed to student growth and development:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#trips&#34;&gt;Leading student professional development trips&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#comps&#34;&gt;Advising student participation in regional and national competitions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#letters&#34;&gt;Writing letters of recommendation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#research&#34;&gt;Mentoring students during independent research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#speakers&#34;&gt;Bringing distinguished speakers to Winona State&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;trips&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-led-professional-development-trips&#34;&gt;I led professional development trips&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking students on trips to outside organizations that routinely utilize quantitative analytics is one of my favorite aspects of my job.  Not only do I enjoy the experience of listening to professionals talk about the &amp;lsquo;real world&amp;rsquo; of data analytics, I also greatly enjoy the informal conversations I have with students to and from the events.  The following are trips I have led or co-led during my probationary period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trane Industries; October 2014&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This visit took place on University Improvement Day in October 2014.  This was a great chance for students to see how statistics are applied in the &amp;ldquo;real world.&amp;rdquo;  I drove one of the vehicles we took to the Twin Cities, and enjoyed the chance to chat with students in my vehicle about their experiences in the Math/Stat department and their plans for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;University of Minnesota&amp;rsquo;s Department of Biostatistics Open House; October 2015&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
The University of Minnesota&amp;rsquo;s Department of Biostatistics periodically hosts open houses for prospective students to hear about the biostatistics graduate program, meet their faculty, and tour the department.  I took 4 students to this event, and it was a very enjoyable and informative experience for the students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;SportCon sports analytics conference, January 2017&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hosted by MinneAnalytics, SportCon was a conference centered on providing data solutions in sports contexts.  I took 5 students to this conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;St. Olaf University; February 2018&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Julie Legler from St. Olaf contacted me in February 2018.  She had encountered &lt;a href=&#34;https://iase-web.org/documents/papers/rt2016/Bergen.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the paper&lt;/a&gt; I gave at the IASE roundtable in Berlin in 2016, and was interested in the work I have done implementing large data sets with social justice themes in my statistics and data science courses.  After corresponding with her, she invited me to bring some WSU students who had been working on class projects that used this data to present their work to her research workshop class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/post/about-social-justice/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a blog post&lt;/a&gt; about this experience, and also thanks to encouragement from Dr. Legler, &lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/project/social-justice-data/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;compiled all the resources&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve used over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Minnesota Twins baseball operations; November 2018&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/twins.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2018, Chris Malone and I took nine students to visit the Minnesota Twins&amp;rsquo; baseball operations.  I organized this trip after reaching out to Director of Baseball Operations Daniel Adler, who graciously agreed to host us for a couple on a Friday morning to hold a Q&amp;amp;A session with students.  This was a fantastic sneak peak behind the curtain of how a Major League front office makes evidence-based decisions on trades, player development, and drafting. One of the perks of the visit was a personal tour of Target Field in the offseason!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;comps&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-1&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-advised-student-participation-in-regional-and-national-competitions&#34;&gt;I advised student participation in regional and national competitions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/minnemudac2017.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;
      &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;b&gt; &lt;em&gt; Winona State University undergraduates made a great impression at the 2017 MinneMUDAC data analytics competition &lt;/em&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
     &lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have helped to advise undergraduate teams in the following regional and national analytics competitions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://minneanalytics.org/hundreds-participate-in-mudac-2017/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MUDAC 2017&lt;/a&gt;.  One team won &amp;ldquo;Best overall,&amp;rdquo; another &amp;ldquo;Best prediction.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://minneanalytics.org/more-than-60-teams-present-findings-at-minnemudac-2017/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MinneMUDAC 2017&lt;/a&gt;.  Three teams advanced to final round. One team won &amp;ldquo;Best overall&amp;rdquo; and another the award for &amp;ldquo;Analytic acumen.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Police data challenge, 2017.    &lt;a href=&#34;http://thisisstatistics.org/police-data-challenge-congratulations-to-our-winners/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Press
        Release&lt;/a&gt; |  &lt;a href=&#34;http://thisisstatistics.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/Best-Overall-College-.pptx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Winning
        presentation&lt;/a&gt; (Described in more detail in my &lt;a href=&#34;../crit1/#dsci310&#34;&gt;Criterion 1 narrative&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://minneanalytics.org/future-data-scientists-provide-insights-at-mudac-2018/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MUDAC 2018&lt;/a&gt;.  Three teams.  Two of the teams advanced to final round (out of 25 teams); one won &amp;ldquo;Best Overall.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://minneanalytics.org/minnemudac/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MinneMUDAC 2018&lt;/a&gt;. Three teams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/mudac2017.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;
      &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;b&gt; &lt;em&gt; The &#34;Best Overall&#34; team from Winona State in MUDAC 2017 with their advisor.  From left to right: Joe Zemmels; Mahzabin Khan; Sierra Suhr; Shane &lt;/em&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
     &lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;letters&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-2&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-wrote-recommendation-letters&#34;&gt;I wrote recommendation letters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take very seriously the responsibility and privilege of writing letters of recommendation for our students.  These letters are the wings on which our students &amp;ldquo;fly the nest&amp;rdquo; and move on to the next stage of their careers in the workforce or graduate school.  Below is a list of the students for whom I have written letters during my probationary period. Often I am able to offer support at multiple times and places along a student&amp;rsquo;s journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Megan Aadland &lt;sup&gt; 1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Austin    Ellingworth&lt;sup&gt; 1,2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grant Gill &lt;sup&gt; 4 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jenn  Halbleib  &lt;sup&gt; 1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andy  Hansen  &lt;sup&gt; 1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jimmy Hickey  &lt;sup&gt; 1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mahzabin  Khan  &lt;sup&gt; 1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gabe  Mancino-Ball &lt;sup&gt; 1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maxene    Meier &lt;sup&gt; 1, 3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stacey    Miertschin &lt;sup&gt; 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sierra    Suhr &lt;sup&gt; 1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eva   Tourangeau &lt;sup&gt; 1, 6 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yulun Xu &lt;sup&gt; 1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt; 1 &lt;/sup&gt; Graduate school&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt; 2 &lt;/sup&gt; Summer Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt; 3 &lt;/sup&gt; Summer Institute in Biostatistics&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt; 4 &lt;/sup&gt; WSU Foundation Scholarships&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt; 5 &lt;/sup&gt; Travel Study opportunities&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt; 6 &lt;/sup&gt; Data Science for Social Good  fellowship&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;research&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-3&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-mentored-students-in-independent-research&#34;&gt;I mentored students in independent research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Capstone projects&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have advised numerous capstone projects for our statistics and data science graduates.  Listed below are all students I have advised during my probationary period.  &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Emphasized projects indicate above-average student work&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2015-16:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/8p16edyvoyt4fkz/Dodd-capstone-final.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jake Dodd: Projecting on-base percentage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/qlq50sv83pdlznm/Final%20Capstone%20-%20Analyzing%20Video%20Game%20Sales.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;John Emerson: Analyzing video game sales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/7idnm5kh1ppih5t/CapstonePoster_Prieur.pptx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stacey Prieur: Biomarkers of inflammation and mortality in the Cardiovascular Health Study&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2016-17:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/fls8fzmx72lf49o/poster.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nick Schroeder, Measuring and modeling batted ball quality&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/zlukx8vjt4hh5qr/ShaneWill_Poster_final.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shane Will, Applications of clustering to finance data&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/ril537m4nz23coz/capstonepres.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tyler Kelemen, Applying supervised learning methods to baseball data.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;float: left; clear: left&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/schroeder.jpg&#34; width=&#34;350&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;float: right; clear: right&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;../../img/shane.jpg&#34; width=&#34;350&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;b&gt; &lt;em&gt; Nick Schroeder and Shane Will present their capstones at the 2017 Ramaley Celebration of Research &lt;/em&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2017-18:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/vujud5rkmc7zvw0/Overwatch%20Capstone%20Poster.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;David Stampley, A Measure of Skill: Analyzing an Overwatch Player&amp;rsquo;s Skillset&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/inos9zomfhzxozm/Capstone%20Poster%20Final.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Courtney Steinmueller, Parametric Weibull Survival Regression Model of Coronary Heart Disease&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/david_courtney.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt; 
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;b&gt; &lt;em&gt; David Stampley and Courtney Steinmueller beside their capstone research posters at the 2018 Ramaley Celebration of Research &lt;/em&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2018-19:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/1zggfqq0ii0atd2/Poster.pptx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rounak Kejriwal, Health insurance prices in the U.S.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;WINSTATS REU&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to Summer 2017, I spearheaded a successful application for Winona State University to host a 10-week Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) in collaboration with Chris Malone and Brant Deppa. The REU was awarded by the American Statistical Association (ASA) through a competitive application process, and provided funding and support to bring 4 undergraduate students to learn about data analysis as a science and profession.  Winona State was one of only 9 universities total (3 each for Summers 2016, 2017, and 2018) to be awarded this REU, which was intended to encourage women, minorities, and persons with disabilities to learn more about STEM fields. (&lt;a href=&#34;http://magazine.amstat.org/blog/2018/09/01/reu18/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;More details at this ASA blog post&lt;/a&gt;.) We began recruiting for our REU in August 2016 and received over 30 very strong applications from students nationwide.  We ultimately extended invitations to 4 exceptional students who all accepted our invitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students partnered with researchers at the Integrated Public Use Microdata Series International (IPUMS-I) to develop data products and visualizations for IPUMS-I users. Two students worked primarily on using multiple correspondence analysis to develop an index of household wealth, while the other two worked on an interactive data visualization to summarize basic demographic information for countries of interest to IPUMS-I users. Both projects required a great deal of data cleaning after extracting the microdata from the IPUMS-I query service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with their research, the students took several professional development trips to learn about applications of data analytics in the workplace. These included visits to Mayo Clinic, Be the Match, Optum, the Wilder Foundation, and the Minnesota Wild.  They also visited the University of Iowa statistics and biostatistics graduate programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the summer, the students traveled to Baltimore to present their research at the 2017 Joint Statistical Meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/files/JSM-Poster.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JSM poster presentation #1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://driftlessdata.space/files/JSM_Poster_Presentation.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JSM poster presentation #2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have continued to stay in touch with and support these students as they continue their professional development.  One of the students went on to pursue a master&amp;rsquo;s degree at University of Iowa after visiting there during the REU.  I am also currently in the recommendation-writing cycle for one of the other students who hopes to pursue a PhD in statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are responses from the students about their experience from a post-REU survey:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What were your favorite aspects of the REU?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Visiting all the companies and the grad school really helped put the career of a statistician in perspective for me. Also, the support from faculty was really great.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How much individual instruction and attention we got from all of the professors. There were four students total, and we worked with four professors, which seems unheard of. You all also really cared about us and wanted to get to know us. I loved going to the pizza farm and Silas&amp;rsquo;s house and getting to know your families. We also got to know you all as people by joking around in our classroom and asking about each other&amp;rsquo;s lives, which I also think is less common. - Going on the professional development trips. I think those opportunities were what helped me see the route I want to take in my career. I could hear that I needed a lot of statistics to do the coolest stuff at the organizations we visited, and could ask about how many people had graduate degrees and which kinds. Seeing the application of data analytics in various fields was probably the most helpful thing for me this summer. - Living with the other REU students. It&amp;rsquo;s been so nice to have friends to hang out with each evening in our apartment. It would be lonely otherwise. I would say a PI should always suggest the students live together. - Learning SO MUCH STATS at the beginning. I loved getting to hear about so many areas of statistics and also having to practice the skills we were learning about - I feel that I actually have an ok handle on a wide range of statistical topics, all because of your instruction (I&amp;rsquo;ve had no statistics previously, but was able to make my way using MCA for research, do the tasks during the instruction, etc.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There was a strong feeling of community - the faculty really cared about us as students and as individuals. It was a fast-paced learning environment in which I felt challenged and excited to learn more concepts. Rooming with Megan and Eva was a great decision - it was so fun to get to them as friends instead of just coworkers. I loved the town of Winona! It was very welcoming, with lots of outdoor activities and fun places to explore. We did meaningful research with questions about something more than maximizing profit. I really liked using IPUMS data because it had so much complexity and so much information. The work was very flexible - I was able to work where I was most comfortable and at the times I preferred. The professional development trips were so eye opening - I feel like I have a much better idea of what I want to do now. They also gave us a chance to change it up a bit and get out of the same place for a few days, which kept it even more interesting. The learning modules at the beginning taught me so much real statistical knowledge that I feel way more prepared for my upper level statistics courses. The trip to Baltimore was a great end to the REU! It was so much fun and was a great networking experience. Plus, it really gave us something to prepare for and made us really put our findings in a comprehensible display.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The REU was a great experience. I think the most beneficial part was getting a taste for what the field is actually like. The trips we took to various companies gave me insight into potential job opportunities for the future. The grad school visit was also helpful. I learned a lot about grad school in general by talking to the biostatistics and statistics departments at the University of Iowa. The grad school visit along with the visits to companies in the public health sector such as Optum, Mayo Clinic, and Be The Match sparked my interest in biostatistics which I hadn&amp;rsquo;t put much thought into before. Before this summer, I had only analyzed a few basic data sets in R so I didn&amp;rsquo;t have any depth of knowledge on what statisticians actually do. Learning concepts in R for data science and learning about regression and how to clean data was extremely helpful. I was also not familiar with Tableau or the dplyr package which both proved themselves to be useful in the research I did this summer. I also loved living with the other student researchers. They acted as a support system while in Winona. The friendship we formed was special and I think we will stay in contact for years to come. Winona is also the perfect place to spend a summer. The area is beautiful and I enjoyed spending time with the faculty outside of work. I was pleased with each member of our group and I enjoyed working with each and everyone of the researchers and professors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;If the WINSTATS REU were to be repeated, would you recommend other students to apply?  Why/why not?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yes, I would recommend this experience to other students without any hesitation. I feel like I acquired more knowledge this summer than I had in the previous year at school. The professional experiences and conferences are far beyond anything most students would experience in a University setting.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yes, I would. Winona is a very pleasant town in which to spend the summer, the professors make you feel very welcome and comfortable, and it&amp;rsquo;s fun to get to go up to the cities frequently. I felt very happy spending my summer in Minnesota. The WINSTATS REU also gave us so much one-on-one attention with the professors - we got valuable training and advice promptly and consistently, and were able to develop strong relationships with our advisers that I hope will remain strong into the future. The professional development trips exposed us to a wide range of professional settings - nonprofit, large corporation, research university/hospital, sports team, etc, and I learned about jobs I didn&amp;rsquo;t even knew existed. From response to Chris: Overall, the positives FAR outweigh the negatives. We were compensated extremely well for this research program, so the expenses we incurred aren&amp;rsquo;t a huge deal. I&amp;rsquo;ve learned so much about myself, the field of data science/statistics, and what I want to do with my education in the next few years, all because of the work you all put in to make connections for us, find us opportunities, and teach us interesting material. I&amp;rsquo;ve loved this summer, and am sad to see it coming to an end. I&amp;rsquo;ve enjoyed getting to know everyone involved so well, and expect to keep in touch with everyone going forward. Thank you for selecting me for the REU - I feel very thankful to have had this experience.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I would definitely recommend for other students to apply! I learned so much about what I want to do, how I work best, and tons of statistical concepts. The faculty and other students made it so fun with so many outside activities and events planned. Overall, a great summer and a great experience!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yes, absolutely. The professional development offered by the REU was really incredible. Again, I&amp;rsquo;d more enthusiastically recommend this program for students at the freshman/sophomore level and for non-stat majors than juniors/seniors and stat majors. However, I think the REU has opportunities for development for any undergrad. Further, the faculty at Winona is friendly and helpful. I found making those relationships to be very valuable.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;speakers&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-4&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-brought-distinguished-speakers-to-winona-state&#34;&gt;I brought distinguished speakers to Winona State&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#top&#34;&gt;Back to top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spring 2015 I wrote a successful application to bring Alan Schwarz to Winona State as a Lyceum speaker.  In compiling the application I garnered letters of support from students in our own department, the Mass Communications department, and the HERS department.  Best-known for his use of quantitative reasoning in his investigative reporting of the NFL concussion cover-ups, Schwarz&amp;rsquo; student Q&amp;amp;A and Lyceum presentation afforded students majoring in mathematics, statistics, and journalism a chance to interact with someone they might not have otherwise.  The students were very engaged during the student Q&amp;amp;A session, so much so that Alan said our students were some of the most engaged he had ever encountered.  It was a very enjoyable visit for all involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also organizing the math/stat department distinguished speaker for Spring 2019.  We are bringing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thefunctionalart.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Alberto Cairo&lt;/a&gt;, author of &lt;em&gt;The Functional Art&lt;/em&gt; and Knight Chair in Visual Journalism at the School of Communication of the University of Miami (UM).  He has taught in more than 20 countries. Students in our data science program (especially the data visualization course) will greatly benefit from Alberto&amp;rsquo;s visit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criterion 5: Service to the university and community</title>
      <link>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit5/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My emphasis on service to the university and community as part of my professional portfolio has grown over the last couple years.  As the following narrative will demonstrate, many of the activities and leadership opportunities I have assumed have taken place during the latter portion of my probationary period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, I have served the university and community through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#dept&#34;&gt;Participating in and leading department committees&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#univ&#34;&gt;Serving on university-wide committees&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#scc&#34;&gt;Directing the statistical consulting center&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#training&#34;&gt;Running campus training sessions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#sdss&#34;&gt;Helping to organize the 2019 Symposium on Statistics and Data Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;dept&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-participated-in-and-led-department-committees&#34;&gt;I participated in and led department committees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Back to top &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A snapshot of the math/stat department committees in which I have participated are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015-16: Statistics faculty search committee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015-present: Student Opportunities and Social Activities Committee (SOSA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016-present: Recruitment committee (chair)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the 2015-16 search, I was part of the committee that bought in our newest probationary faculty member, Todd Iverson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of SOSA, I have helped to evaluate and award department scholarships and create protocol for student travel support.  I have also helped to organize our annual spaghetti dinner and awards ceremony and host our fall picnic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recruitment committee was formed in Fall 2016, and I have served as the chair of this committee since its inception.  This committee has been very active in recruiting prospective students, and we have seen an increase in incoming first-year students declaring majors in our department.  As chair of this committee, in addition to calling meeting, I worked with Creative Services to develop two post-cards to send to prospective students who had declared interest in majors within our department.  One of these featured a photograph of four current (at the time) students, which I took outside Gildemeister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../files/postcard1.png&#34;&gt;Post card #1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../files/postcard2.pdf&#34;&gt;Post card #2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conjunction with the post cards, I have worked to &lt;a href=&#34;../../files/Recruitment_Shirt.jpg&#34;&gt;design t-shirts&lt;/a&gt; that we now send to all students who have been admitted to Winona State with a stated interested in one of the programs in our department.  When these students visit campus, the recruitment committee hosts &lt;a href=&#34;../../files/Student-Admit-Day-2-2-18.pdf&#34;&gt;informational sessions&lt;/a&gt; about our programs and campus-wide opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recruitment committee has also held numerous recruitment workshops.  In October 2017, I worked with Brett Veninga (a connection through MinneAnalytics) to bring several high school students to Winona State for a data anlytics learning experience.  This event consisted of a student case study data analysis, a student panel, and presentation (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kG1dG7-m_2E&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link to video of event&lt;/a&gt;).  The recruitment committee also organized the first-annual &lt;a href=&#34;../../files/math_in_real_world.pdf&#34;&gt;Math in the Real World&lt;/a&gt; workshop which took place during the October 2018 University Improvement Day.  This workshop brought in over 40 students from local high schools to participate in brief, interactive workshop sessions hosted by the department faculty (&lt;a href=&#34;../../files/Workshop_Abstracts.pdf&#34;&gt;link to session descriptions&lt;/a&gt;).  Overall the committee felt the first iteration was a great success and we plan to improve upon it in future years.  Below are some comments from high school teachers regarding the workshop:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Students (and teachers) were made aware of the fact that if you are good at math and/or enjoy it, there are math fields other than teaching or engineering that are relevant and exciting!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I thought it was tremendous!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Students were given real-life examples of where the math they are/will be learning can be used to solve problems. Workshops were great as professors weren&amp;rsquo;t using too complex of math concepts, high school students who maybe aren&amp;rsquo;t entirely in love with math or A+ students are still able to follow along and get something out of it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I really enjoyed what you all did for putting this on for a first time. Workshops were perfect length, the ones we went to were relatable to stuff students have seen or will be seeing in their classes and in the world around them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;univ&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-1&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-served-on-university-wide-committees&#34;&gt;I served on university-wide committees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Back to top &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have served on three all-campus committees during my probationary period:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grade appeals committee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lyceum committee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Student affairs committee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My membership is current on all of these committee.  I value these opportunities not only for the experience and service, but as chances to meet faculty and staff and develop collaborations that I might not otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;scc&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-2&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-directed-the-statistical-consulting-center&#34;&gt;I directed the Statistical Consulting Center&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Back to top &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took over the duty of directing the Statistical Consulting Center (SCC) in Spring Semester 2018.  Directing the SCC has afforded me the opportunity to meet and assist a wide variety of students and faculty.  In the table below I list all the clients I have served either directly or in a supervisory capacity.  This list is a subset clients for whom I have either done statistical analysis and written a report or provided training; a list of all clients I have served in smaller capacities would be much longer!  Some of these service opportunities have also resulted in &lt;a href=&#34;../crit2/#articles&#34;&gt;peer-reviewed publications&lt;/a&gt;.  Asterisks (*) denote clients that were served as part of the STAT 370 statistical consulting course I taught in Fall 2018 (I talk in more detail about the STAT 370 course in particular in my &lt;a href=&#34;../crit1/#stat370&#34;&gt;Criterion 1 narrative&lt;/a&gt;).  For these clients, students prepared reports and presentations under my supervision.  Thus, not only has directing the SCC allowed me to serve the university and community, it has provided a channel for students to do the same as part of a valuable learning experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Client&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Department&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Allison Quam&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Library&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bethany Brent&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Education&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Brian Winrow*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Accounting&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Brittany Borhart, Meghan Panek, Jamie Waldera*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nursing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Diane Forsyth&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nursing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ellen Goslee&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nursing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Heather Fye&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Counselor Education&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Naren Selvaratnam&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Education&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jake Hines*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Biology&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jenny Prochnow&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nursing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jada Langer, Katie Eldred, Misha Bozadijieva&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nursing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jessica Nelson and Sara Roslansky&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nursing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Kim Snyder&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Business Administration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Robin Johnson*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nursing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sandy Paddock*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nursing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sara Persinger and Leah Lindbeck*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nursing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sarah Gerard and Whitney Gessert*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nursing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sarah Jackson*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Counselor Education&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following Fall Semester 2018, I sent out a Qualtrics survey to all clients who were served by the SCC either by me directly or through the STAT 370 class.  I received 10 responses.  All 10 respondents &amp;ldquo;Strongly Agreed&amp;rdquo; with the statement &lt;em&gt;I would recommend the SCC to colleagues&lt;/em&gt;.  In addition, some of the clients provided the following written feedback:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The SCC members were professional throughout the entirety of this project. Notes were taken and questions were asked. Students were open and interested in the research, and wanted to understand their role in the process to aid in whichever way I needed. THANK YOU.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The students were professional, the analysis was completed in a timely manner and students provided a nice power point with graphs to depict the results.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In general I really appreciate the SCC and what is offered. I enjoy site/class visits that I can learn along with the students, and that Silas is there to keep everything accurate and on track. This is an extremely valuable asset to WSU and in my opinion it should be maintained with dedicated faculty time by all means necessary.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I found the consultants to be professional and excited to be of assistance. Furthermore, they were committed to helping their client&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I really appreciated the help from the consulting center. It was nice to work with students as well since they are learning the same way we are. I also really appreciated the second meeting since I was unable to attend the presentation by the students due to illness. The flexibility was nice for me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The SCC did amazing work on my DNP project! Tom and Stacey were in charge of my project and really took the time to understand what I was looking for. They were attentive to my questions and made adjustments accordingly. The box plot they chose to utilize provided an excellent opportunity to not only look at length of orientation in hours, but demonstrated the variability in each population as well. Satisfaction scores were also depicted nicely. I have used their work in my manuscript and plan to submit it to a professional nursing journal for possible publication. My clinical site was very happy with their work and that makes me very happy! I recommended this course to other classmates in the DNP program. Great class and great work!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I thought you were very professional in your face to face interactions and e-mail correspondence. Everything was done in a timely manner.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;training&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-3&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-helped-to-facilitate-campus-training-sessions&#34;&gt;I helped to facilitate campus training sessions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Back to top &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August 2017 I helped to organize a &lt;a href=&#34;https://ntmoore.github.io/2017-08-14-winona/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;software carpentry workshop&lt;/a&gt; for Winona State faculty and students. I specifically wrote and led the portion of the workshop focused on &lt;a href=&#34;https://wsu-datascience.github.io/R-ecology-lesson/04-visualization-ggplot2.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;data visualization with the R package ggplot2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each year between 2015-2018 I also led the Fundamentals of Engineering statisics review session for engineering majors.  In each two-hour session I would lead the students through a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/kpumzm47vgnb09q/Stats%20review.docx?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;set of problems&lt;/a&gt; to help them prepare for their FE exam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;sdss&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;br-4&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-am-co-organizing-the-2019-symposium-on-statistics-and-data-science&#34;&gt;I am co-organizing the 2019 Symposium on Statistics and Data Science&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Back to top &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Summer 2018, Dr. Kelly McConville from Reed College asked me to help co-organize the data visualization track of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/sdss/2019/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2019 Symposium on Statistics and Data Science&lt;/a&gt; in Bellevue, Washington.  She had me in mind to help organize the symposium since seeing my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.causeweb.org/cause/webinar/teaching/2016-12&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2016 webinar&lt;/a&gt; on teaching data visualization.  Co-organizing the data visualization track entails organizing invited sessions and invited session organizers and grouping contributed abstracts into cohesive sessions.  I am very excited for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/sdss/2019/onlineprogram/Program.cfm?TrackID=27&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;excellent slate of sessions&lt;/a&gt; we have on tap for the data visualization session.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
