<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Narratives on Portfolio</title>
    <link>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Narratives on Portfolio</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Statements of support</title>
      <link>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/testimonials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/testimonials/</guid>
      <description>Colleagues The following are letters of support from colleagues with whom I have collaborated during my probationary period.
 Diane Forsyth Jake Hines Allison Quam  Students  
Finally, Jimmy Hickey went above and beyond in his gracious support of my application.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criterion 1: Teaching Effectiveness</title>
      <link>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit1/</guid>
      <description>Outline  Introduction What is effective teaching? I taught statistical thinking, integrating real data with a context and purpose I fostered active learning in all my statistics classes I mapped student learning outcomes to GEP Goal 4 criteria I implemented computational problem-solving in upper-level statistics courses I developed curricula for DSCI 310 and taught its first three offerings I was a motivating, passionate, and helpful instructor in all my courses   Introduction In 2005 I embarked on a double-major in statistics and piano performance at Winona State.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criterion 2: Scholarship and Creative Achievement</title>
      <link>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit2/</guid>
      <description>Introduction As the following narrative will demonstrate, the focus of my scholarship and creative achievement has evolved over the course of my probationary period. Early on, I was focused on finshing up and publishing some of my PhD research on measurement error correction methods in air pollution epidemiology studies. This resulted in several conventional peer-reviewed articles in well-reputed journals. After finding closure in that line of research, my interests turned to data visualization as I was deeply immersed in developing DSCI 310: data summarization and visualization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criterion 3: Continuing preparation and study</title>
      <link>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit3/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I have learned so much during my probationary period at Winona State! One of the aspects of my job for which I am so grateful is the daily opportunity to learn. &amp;ldquo;Boredom&amp;rdquo; is unfortunately a common companion for many people at their work; I am so gratified to say I am not one of these people. In the following narrative I will provide evidence of ways in which I have continued to learn and grow as a professional in my field.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criterion 4: Contributions to student growth and development</title>
      <link>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit4/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Of the five criterion narratives, this the one I have most been looking forward to writing. In many ways, my desire to invest in a career centered around teaching was (and is) fueled by an excitement about making a significant and positive difference in the lives of students during a formative period of their life&amp;rsquo;s arc. Much of this happens in the classroom, but there is so much that takes place outside the classroom walls: in my office, in a van on the way to a field trip, over a celebratory beer at the final semester&amp;rsquo;s end, in the time spent crafting a letter on whose wings the recipient will advance toward graduate school.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criterion 5: Service to the university and community</title>
      <link>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://silasbergen.github.io/tenure_promotion/narratives/crit5/</guid>
      <description>Introduction My emphasis on service to the university and community as part of my professional portfolio has grown over the last couple years. As the following narrative will demonstrate, many of the activities and leadership opportunities I have assumed have taken place during the latter portion of my probationary period.
Specifically, I have served the university and community through:
 Participating in and leading department committees Serving on university-wide committees Directing the statistical consulting center Running campus training sessions Helping to organize the 2019 Symposium on Statistics and Data Science    I participated in and led department committees Back to top</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>